<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Budget Res. No. 2024-04">
  <num>2024-04</num>
  <heading>FY 2025 Budget Modification #1</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-12-20</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-12-19</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-04.pdf">Budget Res. No. 2024-04</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Budget Resolution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council modifying the Annual Budget of the Tribe for Fiscal Year 2025; providing short title; describing purpose; making findings; adopting an amended budget; and providing an effective date.</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Council held this 19 day of December, 2024, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council (the "Council") is vested with the authority to enact Budget Resolutions for the purpose of passing an Annual Budget or Budget Modifications by <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(c)">Article VII, Section 4(c)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Council now finds that, due to a surplus of expected revenues, it is both necessary and expedient to modify the Annual Budget for Fiscal Year 2025;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED:</conjunction>
      <text/>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <section>
    <num>1</num>
    <heading>Short Title.</heading>
    <text>This Budget Resolution shall be known and may be cited as "FY 2025 Budget Modification #1"</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>2</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this Budget Resolution is to account for and appropriate certain revenues received in excess of the amounts forecasted in the Annual Budget for FY 2025 was initially enacted</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>3</num>
    <heading>Findings.</heading>
    <text>The Council hereby finds and decares as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Council is vested with the power to enact Budget Resolutions for the purpose of passing an Annual Budget or Budget Modifications by <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(c)">Article VII, Section 4(c)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Council is vested with the power to raise revenues and appropriate funds for expenditure by <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(b)">Article VII, Section 4(b)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Tribe has received revenue in excess of the amounts forecasted in the Annual Budget for Fiscal Year 2025.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>It is now necessary and expedient to enact a Budget Modification to account for an appropriate said excess revenues.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>4</num>
    <heading>Adoption and Approval.</heading>
    <text>This Council hereby adopts and approves the Budget Modification attached hereto</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>5</num>
    <heading>Effective Date.</heading>
    <text>The Budget Resolution shall be in force and of effect immediately from and after its passage and approval according to law</text>
  </section>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 19 day of December, 2024, at a General Meeting with a vote of <u>6</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>1</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
