<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribal Code of Law">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>4</num>
  <heading>Administration</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>1</num>
    <heading>General Provisions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>100</num>
      <heading>Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="4">This title</cite> shall be known as the "Departmental Organization Act."</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|I|1-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>101</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text><cite path="4">This title</cite> is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (also referred to herein as "Tribe") and pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>, which confers all  Legislative power of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe in the Council of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, and expressly empowers the Council to "to create departments, boards, and commissions located in the Executive branch of government by law" (<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII, §4(d)</cite>); and with "authority to confirm a nominee presented to the Council by the Chief, subject to final installation of the nominee into office by the Chief" (<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">Article VII, § 4(i)</cite>).</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|I|1-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>102</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text><cite path="4">This title</cite> is enacted to establish various departments in the Executive Branch of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, in order to appropriately administer Tribal programs and laws.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|I|1-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>103</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="4">this title</cite> shall be effective upon the date signed by the Chief of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, or upon the date of a veto override by the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|I|1-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>104</num>
      <heading>Interpretation</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="4">this title</cite> shall be interpreted to be in accordance with tribal customary law. Whenever there is uncertainty or a question as to the interpretation of certain provisions of <cite path="4">this title</cite>, tribal law and custom shall be controlling, and where appropriate, may be based on the written or oral testimony of a qualified tribal elder, tribal historian, or tribal representative. If the traditions and customs of the Tribe are inconclusive in any matter, the Court shall construe it consistently with applicable textual tribal law. In the absence of applicable tribal customary law or textual tribal law, the Court shall construe it consistently with applicable law of other jurisdictions.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|I|1-5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>105</num>
      <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
      <text>If any section, provision, or portion of <cite path="4">this title</cite> is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of <cite path="4">this title</cite> shall not be affected thereby.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|I|1-7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>2</num>
    <heading>General Departmental Provisions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>200</num>
      <heading>Removal of Departmental Secretaries</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <heading>Removal by Chief.</heading>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, or any contractual agreements between a Secretary and the Chief, any Secretary may be removed by the Chief at his discretion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <heading>Grounds for Removal by Council.</heading>
        <text>A Secretary may be removed by the Council from their position on the following grounds:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Malfeasance, misfeasance, or nonfeasance of office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>conviction by any court of any crime involving moral turpitude; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>any other grounds as established by Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <heading>Process.</heading>
        <text>The Council shall have the power to remove a Secretary except as may be otherwise provided by law.  The process for the removal of a Secretary by the Council shall be as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>the Council may recommend removal of a Secretary from their position through passage of an official resolution setting forth the grounds for removal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>the Council, after passage of the resolution outlined in subsection (a) of <cite path="§2-1" proof="needed" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11">this Section</cite>, shall set a hearing date to consider the removal of the Secretary and notify the alleged Secretary in writing by certified mail, return receipt requested.  The hearing shall occur no more than ninety (90) days after passage of the resolution outlined in subsection (a) of <cite path="§2-1" proof="needed" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11">this Section</cite>, and the hearing notice shall occur no less than thirty (30) days before the hearing date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>at the hearing, the alleged Secretary shall have the right to protest the removal and defend the allegations against him or her, including the right to cross-examine any witnesses who testify against him or her, and shall have the right to be represented by an attorney or other advocate licensed to practice law before the Upper Mattaponi Tribe's courts; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>after the presentation of evidence at the hearing, the Council may remove the Secretary from their position upon a two-thirds majority vote of the entire Council, absent or present.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Any Secretary removed pursuant to <cite path="§2-1" proof="needed" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11">this Section</cite> may not be reappointed to that same position for a period of two (2) years following removal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|II|2-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>201</num>
      <heading>Reporting</heading>
      <text>Secretaries, as officers of the Executive Branch of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, shall report to the Chief, except as otherwise provided in Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|II|2-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>202</num>
      <heading>Records</heading>
      <text>Departments shall comply with all record retention requirements under Upper Mattaponi Law.  Additionally, Departments shall maintain their records on-site for a period of three (3) years before transferring the documents to the Tribe's long-term records storage facility.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|II|2-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>203</num>
      <heading>Annual Report</heading>
      <text>Secretaries established by <cite path="4">this title</cite> shall be responsible for providing an Annual Report of the Department's activities to the Council and the Chief by the first day of January of each year covering the activities of the prior year.  The report should explain the finances of the Department, identify any current or future liabilities, and any other material items required by Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|II|2-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>204</num>
      <heading>Departmental Decisions</heading>
      <text>Departmental Decisions that affect the rights or liabilities of any person or entity must have a rational basis in fact and be supported by substantial evidence. Such Departmental Decisions must be mailed to said affected individuals within ten (10) days of the date of said decision by Certified United States Mail, Return Receipt Requested with Restricted Delivery.  If a Departmental Decision is not timely mailed to the person or persons affected, it shall have no effect.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|II|2-5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>205</num>
      <heading>Appeals of Departmental Decisions</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided by Upper Mattaponi Law, any individual adversely affected by a Departmental Decision shall have the right to appeal said decision to the Trial Court of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe within thirty (30) days of notice of the decision.  In no event shall the Trial Court hear any appeal that is filed more than one-hundred eighty (180) days after the date of the Departmental Decision.  The Trial Court may establish procedures for consideration of appeals of Departmental Decisions, so long as such procedures provide affected individuals with due process of law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|II|2-6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>206</num>
      <heading>Sovereign Immunity</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe is a sovereign Indian Nation that is immune from suit.  Nothing in this Act waives or impairs the Tribe's immunity from suit.  As an instrumentality of the Tribe, Departments also enjoy immunity from suit except as expressly provided by Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Departments shall not have the authority to waive or otherwise impair the sovereign immunity of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.  The sovereign immunity of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe may only be waived, or otherwise impaired, pursuant to the provisions of Article XIII of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|II|2-7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3</num>
    <heading>Environmental Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>300</num>
      <text>The Environmental Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Environmental Department will be responsible for administering and enforcing the environmental laws of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|III|3-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>301</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Environmental Department shall be to protect human health and the environment by working to ensure citizens have access to clean air, land and water.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|III|3-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>302</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Environmental Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Environmental Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|III|3-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>303</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Environmental Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(d)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(i)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in a field related to environmental sciences;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|III|3-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>4</num>
    <heading>Cultural Protection Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>400</num>
      <text>The Cultural Protection Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Cultural Protection Department will be responsible for the preservation of the Tribe’s cultural heritage along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.  The Department may accomplish this through lectures, discussions, workshops, classes, demonstrations, or working to repatriate lost artifacts of the Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IV|4-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>401</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Cultural Protection Department shall be to preserve and showcase the Tribe's natural and cultural heritage, including language, traditions, and artwork, to strengthen the Tribe's identity.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IV|4-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>402</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Cultural Protection Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Cultural Protection Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IV|4-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>403</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Cultural Protection Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(d)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(i)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in a field related to cultural protection or understanding or comparable work experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IV|4-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5</num>
    <heading>Housing Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>500</num>
      <text>The Housing Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Housing Department will be responsible for administering and applying the Tribe's housing laws and programs along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|V|5-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>501</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Housing Department shall be to provide the Tribe’s citizens with safe, quality housing.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|V|5-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>502</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Housing Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Housing Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|V|5-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>503</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Housing Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(d)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(i)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in a field related to public administration or understanding or comparable work experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|V|5-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>6</num>
    <heading>Community Services Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>600</num>
      <text>The Community Services Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Community Services Department will be responsible for administering and applying laws and programs of the Tribe designed to protect against abuse of elders or children, assist with the care of children and elders, nutrition, and food distribution, along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VI|6-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>601</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Community Services Department shall be to provide assistance and resources to Tribal children, families, elders, and people with disabilities.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VI|6-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>602</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Community Services Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Community Services Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VI|6-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>603</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Community Services Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(d)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(i)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in a field related to social work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VI|6-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>7</num>
    <heading>Enrollment Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>700</num>
      <text>The Enrollment Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Enrollment Department will be responsible for maintaining the citizenship rolls of the Tribe, including enrolling new citizens and maintain accurate voter lists in collaboration with the Tribe's Election Commission, along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VII|7-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>701</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Enrollment Department shall be to quickly and accurately enroll new tribal citizens and maintain accurate tribal citizenship records.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VII|7-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>702</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Enrollment Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Enrollment Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VII|7-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>703</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Enrollment Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(d)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(i)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in a field related to public administration or understanding or comparable work experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VII|7-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>8</num>
    <heading>Education Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>800</num>
      <text>The Education Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Education Department will be responsible for administering programs to provide educational assistance, support, and encouragement, along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VIII|8-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>801</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Education Department shall be to address the education and cultural needs of tribal citizens of all ages.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VIII|8-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>802</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Education Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Education Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VIII|8-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>803</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Education Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(d)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(i)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in a field related to public education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|VIII|8-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>9</num>
    <heading>Facilities &amp; Infrastructure Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>900</num>
      <text>The Facilities &amp; Infrastructure Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Facilities &amp; Infrastructure Department will be responsible for administering programs to maintain the Tribe's buildings, roads, bridges, and other infrastructure, along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IX|9-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>901</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Facilities &amp; Infrastructure Department shall be to ensure a safe and healthy environment for employees, visitors, and residents of the Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IX|9-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>902</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Facilities &amp; Infrastructure Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Facilities &amp; Infrastructure Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IX|9-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>903</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Facilities &amp; Infrastructure Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(D)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(I)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in any field, or ten (10) years of education, training, and work experience in facilities management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|IX|9-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>10</num>
    <heading>Human Resources Department</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1000</num>
      <text>The Human Resources Department of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is hereby created.  The Human Resources Department will be responsible for the hiring and training of all Tribal employees, including managing transfers of employees between departments, along with any other responsibilities under Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|X|10-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1001</num>
      <heading>Mission</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Human Resources Department shall be to support the Tribe and its employees through all phases of employee to ensure a healthy employment relationship.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|X|10-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1002</num>
      <heading>Organization</heading>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided under Upper Mattaponi Law, the Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Human Resources Department in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Human Resources Department from time to time.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|X|10-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1003</num>
      <heading>Secretary</heading>
      <text>The Human Resources Department shall be managed and operated by a Secretary who shall be appointed by the Chief and confirmed by the Council in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(d)">Article VII §§ 4(d)</cite> and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(i)">(i)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.  The Secretary should meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's degree in a field related to human resources or business administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Five (5) years experience in a management role;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Three (3) years experience in budgeting and financial management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-02" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-11" eff="2024-01-02" path="attachments|law|X|10-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>11</num>
    <heading>The Department of Health Enabling Act</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1100</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="4|11">This chapter</cite> shall be known as the Department of Health Enabling Act ("Act").</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-03" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|101" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1101</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="4|11">this chapter</cite> is to establish the Department of Health.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-03" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|102" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1102</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>reorganizing the structure of governmental departments and programs in accordance with the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite> will promote efficiency within the Tribe; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>establishing a Department of Health within the executive branch of government will assist the Tribe in managing, administering, and evaluating various health care programs for the benefit of citizens of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-03" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|103" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1103</num>
      <heading>Organization of the Department of Health</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Department of Health in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Department of Health from time to time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Department of Health may include the following programs, services, and activities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Primary Care Medical Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Dental Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Behavioral and Mental Health Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Public Health Nursing and Other Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Administration</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Any other program or service established by the Chief, subject to ratification by the Council.</em>
          </text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-03" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|104" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1104</num>
      <heading>Department of Health Goals and Objectives</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Department of Health is to assess and implement various health care programs of the Tribe in a well-coordinated and collaborative manner that will enhance educational awareness, disease prevention, and healthy behavioral changes. The primary goal of the Department of Health is to provide comprehensive health care awareness that will target multiple dimensions of health such as physical, mental, emotional, and social needs of citizens of the Tribe of all ages.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-03" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|105" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1105</num>
      <heading>Authority to Operate and Administer the Department of Health</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Chief, and any person(s) designated by the Chief and working at the direction of the Chief, shall have the authority to operate and manage the Department of Health and/or any portion or component of the Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Chief, and any person(s) designated by the Chief and working at the direction of the Chief, shall have the authority to administer the authorized funds appropriated for the Department of Health or its subdivisions,</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>NOTES:</strong>
      </text>
      <text>
        <strong>Primary Care Medical Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of primary healthcare services, appropriate for a local medical center to prevent and treat disease and injury and to promote improvements in health status and outcomes. All medical services, treatments, and laboratory services provided to pediatric and adult patients include the coordination of referrals to outside services not available at the clinic. Primary Care Medical Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Family Health Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Diabetes Treatment and Prevention services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Laboratory Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>Pharmaceutical Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>Telemedicine Services 6. Eldercare Services</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Dental Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of dental services, appropriate for a local dental center to prevent and treat disease and promote improvements in dental health. All dental services, treatment, and laboratory services provided to pediatric and adult patients include the coordination of referrals to outside service not available at the dental clinic. Dental Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>Preventive Care - Checkups, Cleaning and Deep Cleaning</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(I)</num>
        <text>Restorative Services - Fillings, Crowns and Bridges</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(J)</num>
        <text>Dentures</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(K)</num>
        <text>Pediatric</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Behavioral Health and Mental Health Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of behavioral and mental health services, appropriate for our citizens, local school systems, and community at-large. All services and treatments provided to pediatric and adult patients include the coordination of referrals to outside services not available through the Tribe. Behavioral and Mental Health Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(L)</num>
        <text>Individual and Family Support Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(M)</num>
        <text>Mental Health Services</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Public Health Nursing and Other Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of home and community-based services, appropriate for ensuring the health and well-being of our citizens and community at-large. Public Health Nursing and Other Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(N)</num>
        <text>Health, Education, Health Promotion, and Disease Prevention</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(O)</num>
        <text>Public Health Nursing</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(P)</num>
        <text>Physical Therapy 4. Occupational Therapy</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Q)</num>
        <text>Nutrition and Dietetics</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Administration</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of administrative services, appropriate for the operation of the Health program. All administrative services not provided by Tribal employees will be contracted with outside vendors where appropriate. Administrative services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(R)</num>
        <text>General Administrative Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(S)</num>
        <text>Business Office</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(T)</num>
        <text>Housekeeping Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(U)</num>
        <text>Human Resources</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(V)</num>
        <text>Infection Control Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(W)</num>
        <text>Information Technology</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(X)</num>
        <text>Medical Records</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Y)</num>
        <text>Medical Services Administration</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Z)</num>
        <text>Patient Registration</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-03" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|106" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1106</num>
      <heading>Procurement Policy</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall have the authority to establish and modify a written procurement policy for the Department of Health and/or its subdivisions. Any modification to an existing procurement policy for the Department of Health shall be provided to the Council within thirty days of approval by the Chief.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Any procurement policy for the Department of Health approved by the Chief shall include the following provisions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any other procurement policy or resolution adopted by the Tribe, the Department of Health is authorized to negotiate, execute and otherwise conclude, and administer contracts and agreements in accordance with appropriated funds as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text><u>Operational Contracts</u>: for goods and services, including those with state and federal agencies ("intergovernmental agreements"), that are necessary to maintain operations, services, and to comply with Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services ("CMS") conditions of participation (collectively, "Operational Contracts"); and,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><u>Revenue Contracts</u>: with insurance providers, third-party administrators, and other similar type of patient benefit providers that are necessary for the Department of Health to submit claims and receive payment for services (collectively, "Revenue Contracts").</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's liability for an Operational Contract or Revenue Contract entered pursuant to this Act shall not exceed, and sovereign immunity is not waived for, an amount greater than the Tribe's applicable insurance coverage or the total value of the contract, whichever is lower; provided, that the Department of Health shall provide the Council and Chief with an annual written report detailing the number of contracts entered into that included a waiver of sovereign immunity including the purposes and terms of each waiver.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>On a semi-annual basis, the Department of Health shall provide a summary of all current Operational and Revenue Contracts, which shall include a description of the type of services provided under the contract, the total and annual amount of the contract, the duration of the contract, and a current revenue and expenditure report, to the Chief and Council.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-04" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|104" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>12</num>
    <heading>The Planning Office Establishment Act of 2025</heading>
    <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="" type="History"/>
    <section>
      <num>1200</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as, "The Planning Office Establishment Act of 2025" ("Act").</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1201</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to establish a Planning Office to assist the Tribe in preparing and implementing long-range and strategic plans, managing land uses, and developing and submitting grant applications.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1202</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Council has identified the need to develop and/or update a master plan or strategic plans for both long-term and short-term purposes that will address the goals of the Tribe and assist the leaders of the Tribe and the Departments in fulfilling the needs of the Tribe and its citizens.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>A Planning Office is needed to address not only land use and development issues, but also assist the Tribe in preparing and submitting various grant applications for all the Departments and programs within the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1203</num>
      <heading>Planning Office</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>There is hereby established a Planning Office, which shall be located with the Executive branch of government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Planning Office shall be responsible for developing overall plans for the Tribe for both long-term and short-term purposes, which address land use and acquisition issues, potential economic development activities, community development needs, infrastructure assessments, and any other topics identified by the Chief or his designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The Planning Office shall develop a list of grant opportunities available to the Tribe, and shall assist the Tribe and its Departments with the preparation and submission of grant applications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The Council hereby authorizes the establishment of the Planning Office, subject to an appropriation of funds in an Annual Budget or Budget Modification for such purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1412</num>
      <heading>EFFECTIVE DATE</heading>
      <text>This Ordinance shall be in force and of effect immediately from and after its passage and approval according to law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-05-05" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-08" eff="2025-05-05" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|12" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>13</num>
    <heading>The Due Diligence Act of 2025</heading>
    <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
    <section>
      <num>1301</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as, the "The Due Diligence Act of 2025" (the "Act").</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1302</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to establish a formal process for the Tribe to evaluate proposed economic development projects to determine their viability and to reduce risks.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1303</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council finds that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Council has determined that it is in the best interests of the Tribe to identify, promote, and pursue economic development projects; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Tribe has identified the need to establish a process to evaluate potential economic development projects to determine their viability, and their investment and revenue potential in order to minimize risk and the loss of investment funds.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1304</num>
      <heading>Definitions</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of this Act, the following terms shall have the following meanings:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>"Economic Development Project" shall mean a new or expanded business venture of the Tribe, or a tribally-owned business, including the acquisition of real property for use by the business, construction, installation, and rehabilitation of fixtures for the improvement of real estate owned, used, or occupied by the tribal business, provided that the expected cost of the project exceeds fifty-thousand dollars ($50,000.00).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1305</num>
      <heading>Due Diligence</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Chief, or his designee, shall conduct a thorough due diligence investigation and evaluation including preparation of a written "Due Diligence Report" analyzing each potential economic development project under consideration by the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Due Diligence Report shall include, but not be limited to, the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Identification of funding to acquire and complete the project;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A feasibility study analyzing the viability of the businesses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A thorough analysis of the audited financial statements and audits of the existing businesses, if any, for last three years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Projections of revenue for the businesses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>A schedule of accounts payable and accounts receivable for the business, if any;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Other financial information including assets, inventory, debts, liabilities, strategic plan, credit reports, and any internal controls;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>The existing businesses and their organizational structure, if any, including any organic documents, meeting minutes, resolutions, and annual reports;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Any reports provided to the Secretary of State where the business is incorporated, if any, including a Certificate in Good Standing issued by the respective State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>A list of Board of Directors of any existing business, or the proposed structure of a new business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>All assets including physical assets, real property, buildings, equipment of the existing business or that will be required for a new business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>All existing leases, contracts, and other legal documents involving the business, if any;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(12)</num>
          <text>A list of employees and their qualifications, salaries, benefits, personnel policies for an existing business, or such information for a new business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(13)</num>
          <text>Copies of all litigation documents involving the existing business, if any, including any arbitration decisions, during the last five years, and any ongoing litigation or disputes, or threatened litigation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(14)</num>
          <text>Insurance policies in effect and claim history of the business, or the types and estimated costs of insurance for a new business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(15)</num>
          <text>Copies of any permits or licenses that are in effect or that will be required;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(16)</num>
          <text>Detailed reports on any environmental hazards, liabilities, litigation, and any related Federal, State, or local regulatory notices pertaining to an existing business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(17)</num>
          <text>Status of any tax disputes, audits, settlements, liens, and tax filings for the last five years, if any;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(18)</num>
          <text>A list of professional advisors for the business including accounting firms, law firms, consulting firms, and other professionals used by the business, or that will be required;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(19)</num>
          <text>Any customer information maintained by the business or that may be available for the business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(20)</num>
          <text>The identification and estimated costs for realtor services necessary for acquiring the property or initiating the new business; and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(21)</num>
          <text>Any other pertinent information that will assist the Tribe in determining the economic viability of the project.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Chief, or his designee, shall provide copies of each Due Diligence Report individually to each Representative on the Council within ten (10) business days of the completion of said Report.   Chief shall make available for review, upon request of any Representative on the Council, any data or documents relied upon or considered in preparation of the Due Diligence Report.  Unless the Council, or any Representative thereof, notifies the Chief, or his designee, of any deficiencies in the Due Diligence Report within ten (10) business days of receipt thereof, the Due Diligence Report shall be deemed sufficient under this Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>No tribal funds may be used in furtherance of an economic development project until the Due Diligence Report for the project has been provided to the Council.  This shall not apply to any funds expended in preparation of the Due Diligence Report, such as funds expended in market or feasibility studies.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-11-20" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-15" eff="2025-11-20" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>14</num>
    <heading>The Upper Mattaponi Ethics Law</heading>
    <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
    <section>
      <num>1401</num>
      <heading>COMMISSION CREATED</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>There is hereby created an Upper Mattaponi Tribal Ethics Commission ("Commission"). The Commission shall be comprised of three (3) members who shall elect a Chairperson from among their number at their first meeting in each calendar year.  Members of the Commission shall only be enrolled Upper Mattaponi Citizens.  Commissioners shall be nominated by the Chief and confirmed by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Commissioners shall serve for a term of three (3) years with an anniversary date of January 1.  Commissioners shall be automatically reappointed, if a replacement is appointed, within sixty (60) days prior to the expiration of the term.  Once the full Commission is seated, Commissioners shall draw lots to determine which of the members shall serve a one (1) year term, to be called Seat 1, two (2) year term, to be called Seat 2, or three (3) year term, to be called Seat 3.  Thereafter, all members shall serve full three (3) year terms, with one (1) seat being subject to reappointment each subsequent year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Members of the Commission may resign at any time but may be removed by a two-third majority vote of the Upper Mattaponi Council and only upon the following listed grounds:  (a) Conviction or guilty plea entered to a felony involving dishonesty or the disrespect of human life; (b) Conviction or guilty plea entered to a charge of destruction of property, assault or battery upon another person; (c) Conviction or guilty plea entered to a drug or alcohol related charge; or (d) Falsifying information on any tribal or federal application or form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Vacancies shall be filled by the Chief without being confirmed by the Council for the remainder of the respective term.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>No person who is a public official or employee of the Tribe shall serve on the Commission.  No Commissioner shall be eligible for elected office for one (1) year after completing his term.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1402</num>
      <heading>PURPOSE</heading>
      <text>This law is established to require adherence to standards of conduct such that all persons to whom this law applies shall abstain from using any function of their office or duties in a manner which could place, or appear to place, their personal economic or special interests before the interests of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1403</num>
      <heading>DEFINITIONS</heading>
      <text>As used in this Chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>"Affinity" means the relation among a person and the family of such person's spouse because of marriage.  The degrees of Affinity are computed as are the degrees of Consanguinity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>"Business" includes any enterprise, organization, trade, occupation or profession whether or not operated as a legal entity for profit, including any Business, trust, holding company, corporation, partnership, joint venture, or sole proprietorship, Consultant or other self-employed enterprise.  "Business" also includes any Business in which a person subject to this Act or a member of such person's Immediate Family is a director, officer, partner, trustee or Employee, holds any position of management or receives Compensation or Income in any form such as wages, commission, direct or indirect investment worth more than $1,000 or holds any ownership, security or other beneficial interest, individually or combined, amounting to more than ten percent (10%) of said Business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>"Citizen" means an individual officially enrolled with the Upper Mattaponi Tribe as listed on the Tribe's membership roll as of December 1, 2022; a lineal biological descendant of someone on that roll; or a person who proves descent from someone on the July 15, 2003, roll, subject to approval by the Chief and confirmation by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Ethics Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>"Compensation" or "Income" means any money or thing of value received, or to be received as a claim on future services, whether in the form of a fee, salary, expense, allowance, forbearance, forgiveness, interest, dividend, royalty, rent, capital gain, or any other form of recompense or any combination thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>"Confidential Information" means information which by law or practice is not available to the public at large or is deemed Confidential by a Governmental Body.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>"Conflict of Interest" means the reasonable foreseeability or appearance that any personal interest or Economic Interest of a Public Official or Employee of the Tribe will be affected in any materially different manner from the interest of the general public, by any decision, enactment, agreement, award or other official action or function of any Governmental Body or political subdivision of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>"Consanguinity" means relationship by blood; kinship.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(I)</num>
        <text>"Constitution" means the Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe as adopted by the enrolled Citizen voters of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe on July 22, 2023, and amendments thereto.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(J)</num>
        <text>"Consultant" means a person who gives professional, expert, or specialized advice or services for Compensation or Income.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(K)</num>
        <text>"Covered Person" means every Employee, director, officer, partner, trustee, agent, or Contractor of a Business owned in whole or in part by the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, as well as any officer or director of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal government or programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(L)</num>
        <text>"Employee" means any person working for, or rendering or exchanging any services or performing any act for or on behalf of another person, organization or entity in return for any form of pay or other Compensation or Income or any other thing of value received or to be received anytime temporarily, permanently or indefinitely, in any capacity; whether an agent, servant, representative, Consultant, advisor, Independent Contractor or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(M)</num>
        <text>"Employee of the Tribe" means any employee who is temporarily, periodically, permanently or indefinitely in the Employment of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe and/or any Governmental Body thereof, or any wholly or partly owned business of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(N)</num>
        <text>"Employment" means the status or relationship existing or created by and between a person designated or acting as an Employee and the person, organization, group or other entity for whom or on whose behalf any such work, acts, services or other benefit has been, is being or will be rendered or performed for pay or any other form of Compensation or Income.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(O)</num>
        <text>"Economic Interest" means an interest held by a person subject to this Act and/or members of such person's Immediate Family which is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>any ownership, Compensation or Income, investment, security or other beneficial interest in a Business, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>any Employment or prospective Employment for which negotiations have already begun.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(P)</num>
        <text>"Gift" includes any gratuity, special discount, favor, hospitality, payment, loan, subscription, economic opportunity, advance, deposit of money, services, or other benefit received without equivalent consideration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Q)</num>
        <text>"Governmental Body" means any branch, entity, enterprise, authority, division, department, office, commission, council, board, bureau, committee, legislative body, agency, and any other establishment of the Executive, Legislative, and/or Judicial Department of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(R)</num>
        <text>"Immediate Family" includes spouse, father, mother, child, brother or sister or other person when identified as such by tribal customs and traditions or by proper and appropriate authorities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(S)</num>
        <text>"Independent Contractor" or "Contractor" means a person or entity who performs services or completes tasks for Compensation or Income under a contractual agreement with the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(T)</num>
        <text>"Ministerial Action" means an action that a Public Official or Employee of the Tribe performs in a given state of facts in a prescribed manner in obedience to a mandate of legal authority, without regard to, or in the exercise of, such person's own judgment upon the propriety of the action being taken.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(U)</num>
        <text>"Pecuniary" means monetary; relating to money; financial; consisting of money or that which can be valued in money.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(V)</num>
        <text>"Public Office/Official."  "Public Office" means those offices and positions which are elective or appointed in any Governmental Body of the Tribe. "Public Official" means any person holding such office or position.  "Public Official" shall also include any person who has publicly announced an intent to campaign for Public Office, initiated fundraising activities or received funds for such campaign, authorized promotion for, or filed a declaration of candidacy or a petition to appear on the ballot for election as a Public Official; and any person who has been nominated by a Public Official or Governmental Body for appointment to serve in any public capacity, position or office, but who has not yet been seated in such public capacity, position or office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(W)</num>
        <text>"Upper Mattaponi Tribe" or "Tribe" means a federally recognized Tribe of nearly 700 enrolled Citizens, with its headquarters located in King William County, Virginia. The Tribe operates under the Upper Mattaponi Constitution, duly adopted on July 22, 2023, and is recognized by the Secretary of the Interior of the United States as a self-governing, sovereign government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(X)</num>
        <text>"Upper Mattaponi High Court" or "High Court" means the appellate court within the Tribal Judicial Branch consisting of a Chief Justice and two Associate Justices. The High Court has the power to interpret the Constitution and laws of the Tribe, including the authority to declare laws unconstitutional, make conclusions of law, issue remedies in law and equity, and function as a court of record. It serves as the highest judicial authority in the Tribe's court system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Y)</num>
        <text>"Upper Mattaponi Trial Court" or "Trial Court" means the court of original jurisdiction within the Tribal Judicial Branch that hears all cases and controversies, both criminal and civil, arising under the Constitution, laws, and common law of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe. It is comprised of a Chief Judge and other Associate Judges as determined necessary by the Council. The Trial Court has the authority to interpret the Constitution and laws of the Tribe, make findings of fact and conclusions of law, issue all remedies in law and equity, and serve as a court of record. It includes specialized courts such as the Peacemaker Court to resolve civil disputes by agreement of the parties.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1404</num>
      <heading>APPROPRIATION, COMPENSATION, STAFF</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall receive an annual appropriation included in the annual tribal budget sufficient to enable it to perform its duties as set forth herein.  Any funds appropriated to the Commission which remain unspent at the end of the fiscal year shall be returned to the General Fund.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall present its proposed budget to the Chief of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, who shall consider the proposed budget and shall incorporate it as the funds permit in an overall yearly budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Commissioners shall receive reimbursement for travel, lodging and meals while on official business as provided by Tribal policy; otherwise, Commissioners shall be compensated at a rate established by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The Commission may employ an office manager and maintain an office in a location provided by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1405</num>
      <heading>DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES</heading>
      <text>In accordance with all powers and authority as provided in this Ordinance, the Commission shall have the specific duties, responsibilities and authority to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Provide, upon the request of any person who is seeking to comply with this Ordinance, written advisory opinions to guide conduct or address specific questions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Provide written decisions upon hearing complaints, challenges or any other matter as provided by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Conduct administrative hearings to hear complaints and determine violations or noncompliance with this Ordinance or any other ethics requirement.  All Commission hearings shall follow rules of procedure promulgated by the Commission and presented to the Council for its rejection, amendment, alteration and/or approval.  A complainant shall present his own complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Dismiss any complaint which the Commission determines has insufficient facts to constitute a violation of or is in noncompliance with this Ordinance; or provides insufficient evidence to support the allegations; or is otherwise outside the authority of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Issue a written opinion or decision detailing the finding of facts and reasoning, or lack thereof, of any issue heard by the Commission to the complainant and other interested parties including the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1406</num>
      <heading>GENERAL RULES OF PROCEDURE</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise provided by Upper Mattaponi law, no action shall be brought before the Commission more than six (6) months after the facts and circumstances giving rise to the action occurred.  If an action is recurring, each subsequent action will be considered facts and circumstances giving rise to the action for the purposes of calculating six (6) months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Commission may recommend reprimand or removal for any person violating any ethics requirement of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.  Furthermore, the Commission may for a maximum total of 45 days suspend with or without pay (in the Commission's discretion) any person where it has recommended reprimand or removal, but such removal or reprimand has not yet been accomplished.  Regarding the same order, the Commission may not suspend a person twice or more.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Complainant(s) and person(s) who are the subject of ethics complaint(s) have the right to representation by legal counsel who is licensed to practice law, present evidence, to testify in their own behalf, question witnesses against them and call witnesses to testify in support of their respective causes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The burden of proof shall be more likely than not standard and shall be on the complainant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Two (2) Commissioners shall constitute a quorum; except where a unanimous decision is required, decisions shall be made by majority of a quorum.  In the event only two (2) Commissioners are present, decisions shall be made by unanimous vote.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1407</num>
      <heading>ENFORCEMENT</heading>
      <text>If the recommendation of the Commission regarding any decision it has issued is not followed within 60 days, the Commission may within 120 days elect to request a formal written explanation of why the decision is not followed, and no sooner than 30 days thereafter conduct a hearing to determine whether further action is needed.  If further action is deemed needed by a majority vote of the Commission, then the Commission may seek enforcement by filing a civil petition or complaint before the Upper Mattaponi Trial Court.   The decisions of the Upper Mattaponi Trial Court shall be binding and final upon the Upper Mattaponi Tribe and all parties to any decision of the Commission the Upper Mattaponi Trial Court may hear as enforcement.  Appeal to the Upper Mattaponi High Court is permitted of any enforcement decision of the Trial Court. The enforcement decisions of the Commission shall be given substantial deference and shall only be overturned if not rationally related to the facts and circumstances or not warranted in any case by law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1408</num>
      <heading>APPEALS</heading>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Trial Court and no other entity shall have jurisdiction to hear all initial appeals from decisions of the Commission.  The Commission itself may not seek an appeal.  Any person with a legitimate and significant interest impacted by a decision of the Commission may file an appeal with the Upper Mattaponi Trial Court.  Any appeal must be filed within thirty (30) days of the issuance of a decision by the Commission or such appeal will be forever barred.  The decisions of the Upper Mattaponi Trial Court shall be binding and final upon the Upper Mattaponi Tribe and all parties to any decision of the Commission the Upper Mattaponi Trial Court may hear as an appeal.  Appeal to the Upper Mattaponi High Court is permitted of any decision of the Trial Court under this section.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|8" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1409</num>
      <heading>STANDARDS OF CONDUCT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Conduct in Conformity with Applicable Rules and Laws.</text>
        <text>All Covered Persons shall at all times conduct themselves in a manner that reflects credit upon the Upper Mattaponi Tribe and comply with all applicable laws of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe with respect to their conduct in the performance of the duties of their respective office or Employment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>General Prohibitions; Conflicts of Interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>No Covered Person shall use, attempt to use, or appear to use or attempt to use, any official or apparent authority of their office or duties which places, or could reasonably be perceived as placing, their or their Immediate Family's private economic gain or that of any special Business interests with which they are associated, before those of the Tribe whose paramount interest their office or Employment is intended to serve.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Every Covered Person shall avoid any action, whether or not specifically prohibited herein, which could result in, or create an appearance of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>using Public Office for private gain;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>giving preferential treatment to any person or special interest organization;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>impeding governmental efficiency or economy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>losing or compromising complete independence or impartiality of actions; and/or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>making a government decision outside official channels.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Use of Confidential Information for Private Gain.</text>
        <text>No Covered Person shall use or disclose Confidential Information gained in the course of, or by reason of, their official position or activities to further their private Economic Interest or personal interest or that of anyone else.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>Restrictions Against Incompatible Interests or Employment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>Covered Persons shall not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>have direct or indirect financial or other Economic Interests nor engage in such other Employment or economic activity which involves inherent substantial conflict of interest, or has the appearance of involving such inherent substantial conflict of interest with their responsibilities and duties as Public Officials or Employees of the Tribe or one of the Tribe's businesses; nor</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>engage in, directly or indirectly, financial or other economic transactions as a result of, or primarily depending upon, information obtained through their work for or in relation to the Tribe; nor</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>acquire any economic or other financial property, contractual or other Economic Interest at a time when they believe, or have reason to believe, that it will directly and substantially affect or be so affected by their official actions or duties.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>Subject to the restrictions and conditions set forth herein, Covered Persons are free to engage in lawful financial transactions to the same extent as the general public.  Governmental Bodies of the Tribe may, however, adopt further approved restrictions upon such transactions or Employment, as authorized herein and by other applicable laws of the Tribe, in light of special circumstances or the particular duties of such Public Official or Employee of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(I)</num>
        <text>No Business or Governmental Body shall employ a Covered Person if such Employment is prohibited by or otherwise violates any provision of this Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(J)</num>
        <text>The term "Employment" within the meaning of this subsection includes professional services and other services rendered by a Covered Person, whether rendered as an Employee, Consultant or other Independent Contractor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(K)</num>
        <text>Appropriate Actions in Case of Conflict of Interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(L)</num>
        <text>When a Covered Person is required to take official action on a matter in which such Person has a personal Economic Interest, they should first consider eliminating that interest.  If such is not feasible nor required under Subsection D above, such person shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>prepare and sign a written statement describing the matter requiring action and the nature of the potential conflict for inclusion in the official record of any vote or other decision or determination and also for the information of the Commission, immediately upon becoming aware of such matter and potential conflict;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>abstain from voting, sponsoring, influencing or in any manner attempting to influence any vote, official decision or determination which would favor or advance such person's personal Economic Interest in such matter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>abstain from voting or otherwise participating in an official vote, decision or determination of such matter, unless otherwise directed by the authorized residing official of the Governmental Body making such decision or determination, or as otherwise required or allowed by applicable law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(M)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise required or allowed by applicable law, the abstention by a Covered Person from voting or otherwise participating in an official decision or determination of a matter shall not affect the presence of such person for purposes of establishing a quorum necessary for a Body to whom they are a member to take action of voting, deciding or determining such matter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(N)</num>
        <text>If the Covered Person has an immediate supervisor, he or she shall also deliver a copy of such statement described in Subparagraph 1.a above to the Commission and to their immediate superior who shall assign the matter to another person.  If such Employee has no immediate superior, he or she shall take such steps as the Commission shall prescribe or advise to abstain from influencing actions and decisions in the matter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(O)</num>
        <text>In the event that a Covered Person's participation is otherwise legally required or allowed for the action to be made, such Public Official or Employee of the Tribe and appropriate Public Official or immediate superior requiring such participation shall fully report the occurrence to the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(P)</num>
        <text>Tribal Governmental Contracts; Restrictions and Bid Requirements.</text>
        <text>No Covered Person, nor any member of such person's Immediate Family, shall be a party to, nor have an interest in, the profits or benefits of any governmental contract or be the recipient of investment by the Upper Mattaponi Tribe or any business owned in whole or in part by the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, unless the contract or the investment meets the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>the contract or investment is let by notice and competitive bid or other procurement procedures as required under all applicable laws, rules, regulations and policies of the Tribe or other appropriate agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>the entire transaction is conducted at arm's length after written notice has been provided to the Commission regarding the interest of the Covered Person or a member of their Immediate Family; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>the Covered Person has taken no part (including by recusing from any votes) in the determination of whether or not to enter into the specific contract or investment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Q)</num>
        <text>Unauthorized Compensation or Income or Benefit for Official Acts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(R)</num>
        <text>No Covered Person shall accept or receive any benefit, favor or other form of Compensation or Income for performing the official duties of their office or Employment, beyond the amount or value which is authorized and received in their official capacity for performing such duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(S)</num>
        <text>This Section shall not be construed to prohibit the receipt of authorized Compensation or Income for the performance of other distinct and lawful public duties by Public Officials or Employees of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(T)</num>
        <text>Unauthorized personal use of property or funds of the Tribe.</text>
        <text>No Public Official, Employee, or Contractor of the Tribe shall use any property of the Tribe or any other public property of any kind for any use other than as authorized and approved for official purposes and activities.  Such persons shall properly protect and conserve all such property, equipment and supplies which are so entrusted, assigned or issued to them.  The Tribe wishes to create a safe harbor based on practice and custom and acknowledges that Public Officials or Employees may be issued computers, phones, cars, or be provided with or refunded for offices or supplies and same shall not, when used in the ordinary course, be considered unauthorized.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(U)</num>
        <text>Staff Misuse Prohibited.</text>
        <text>Public Officials, Employees, and Contractors of the Tribe shall only utilize Employees of the Tribe and staff only for the official purposes for which they are employed or otherwise retained.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(V)</num>
        <text>Retaliation Prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(W)</num>
        <text>Retaliation against any party or witness to a complaint is hereby prohibited.  Retaliation shall include any unjustified or unsubstantiated form of adverse or punitive action against a complainant, party or witness in an ethics-related cause of action brought before the Commission.  Retaliation is considered an ethics violation in and of itself.  Protection against retaliation shall also be afforded to any person(s), including Commission members and staff, offering testimony or evidence or complying with directives of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(X)</num>
        <text>Any violations of this Section regarding retaliation (Section J) shall be considered obstruction and contempt violations of both the civil and criminal codes of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Y)</num>
        <text>Restrictions Against Gifts or Loans to Influence Official Acts.</text>
        <text>No Covered Person shall solicit or accept for themselves or another, any Gift, including economic opportunity, favor, service, or loan (other than from a regular lending institution on generally available terms) or any other benefit of an aggregate monetary value of one thousand dollars ($1,000) or more over a period of twelve (12) months, from any person, organization or group which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>has, or is seeking to obtain, contractual or other Business or financial relationships or approval from any Governmental Body, office or entity with which the Public Official or Employee of the Tribe is associated or employed, including partly or wholly owned Upper Mattaponi Tribal businesses; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>conducts operations or activities which are regulated or in any manner supervised by any Governmental Body with which the Public Official or Employee of the Tribe is associated or employed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Z)</num>
        <text>Permitted Gifts, Awards, Loans, Reimbursements and Campaign Contributions.  Subsection L above shall not be construed to prohibit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>an occasional non-pecuniary Gift, insignificant in value;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>gifts from, and obviously motivated by, family or social relationships, as among Immediate Family members or family inheritances;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>food and refreshments customarily made available in the ordinary course of meetings where a Covered Person may properly be in attendance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>an award or honor customarily and publicly presented in recognition of public service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>a political campaign contribution, in accordance with all applicable election laws and provided that no promise or commitment regarding the official duties of office or Employment is made in return for such contribution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>gifts of any large value made to the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|9" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1410</num>
      <heading>SANCTIONS; PENALTIES; LEGAL LIABILITIES</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Administrative Sanctions.</text>
        <text>Upon a written finding that there has been an ethical violation, which sets out the factual and legal basis for the finding, the Commission may recommend any single, a combination or all of the following penalties or sanctions, depending upon the severity of the violation:</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>For Public Officials, recommend reprimand, removal, discharge, or termination from office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>For Employees of the Tribe, recommend to the person's Immediate Supervisor for discipline, including suspension without pay or other benefits and dismissal as provided by other laws, regulations and personnel policies or procedures applicable thereto.  If the Employee has no immediate supervisor, then the recommendation shall be made to the Executive Director, who is authorized to implement the recommendation, or modify it as he or she sees fit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>For all Covered Persons, issuance of a private reprimand, which shall be entered into such person's permanent record of Employment or office and upon the permanent record of the Public Office or entity of which such person is a Citizen or Employee of the Tribe, in accordance with provisions of applicable Upper Mattaponi employment law and procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>For all Covered Persons, issuance of a written public reprimand, which shall be entered into such person's permanent record of Employment or office and upon the permanent record of the Public Office or entity of which such person is a Citizen or Employee of the Tribe, according to provisions of applicable Upper Mattaponi law and procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>Any person knowingly and willfully filing any complaint authorized under this Act or by any other applicable law, without just cause or good faith belief and with malice or other improper purpose, including personal, political or other harassment or embarrassment, shall be guilty of a civil offense. For such offense, the Commission may recommend to the Judicial branch the imposition of a fine per occurrence, and shall be responsible for the attorney fees and costs of person wrongfully accused, as well as any attorney fees and costs incurred by the Upper Mattaponi Tribe or the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|10" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1411</num>
      <heading>SEVERABILITY</heading>
      <text>If any provision of this Ordinance or the application of such provision to any person, firm, association, corporation or circumstances shall be held invalid, the remainder of this Act, and the application of such other provisions than those held to be invalid, shall not be affected thereby.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-08-25" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-02" eff="2025-08-25" path="attachments|law|11" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>20</num>
    <heading>Minimum Commission Standards Act</heading>
    <subheading>Subchapter A: General Provisions</subheading>
    <section>
      <num>2001</num>
      <heading>Title.</heading>
      <text>This law shall be known as the "Minimum Commission Standards Act."</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2002</num>
      <heading>Authority.</heading>
      <text>This Act is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe and pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>, which empowers the Council to "create departments, boards, and commissions located in the Executive branch of government by law," Art. VII, Sec. 4(d).</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2003</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text>This Act is enacted to provide general gap-fill provisions governing Commissions created pursuant to Upper Mattaponi Law.  Nothing herein shall restrict the Council's authority to enact procedures and provisions unique to specific Commissions.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2004</num>
      <heading>Effective Date.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this Act shall be effective after ratification by the Council, and upon the date signed by the Chief of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2005</num>
      <heading>Interpretation.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this Act shall be interpreted to be in accordance with tribal customary law. Whenever there is uncertainty or a question as to the interpretation of certain provisions of this Act, tribal law and custom shall be controlling, and where appropriate, may be based on the written or oral testimony of a qualified tribal elder, tribal historian, or tribal representative. If the traditions and customs of the Tribe are inconclusive in any matter, the Court shall construe it consistently with applicable textual tribal law. In the absence of applicable tribal customary law or textual tribal law, the Court may consult applicable federal law and state law if it may be helpful in establishing Upper Mattaponi law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2006</num>
      <heading>Applicability.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this Act apply only to the extent that they do not conflict with any other provision of law.  To the extent that a provision of this Act conflicts with a Commission's Organic Act, the Organic Act takes precedence on that subject matter.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2007</num>
      <text>Severability and Non-Liability.</text>
      <text>If any section, provision, or portion of this Act is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this Act shall not be affected thereby.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2008</num>
      <heading>General Definitions.</heading>
      <text>Any term not defined in this Section shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this Act, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text><strong>"Commission"</strong> means any governmental entity created by Upper Mattaponi law to conduct regulatory matters on behalf of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, regardless of whether the entity is identified as a department, commission, agency, board, etc.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text><strong>"Organic Act"</strong> means the Act of the Council that created the subject Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <subheading>Subchapter B: Organization Of Commissions</subheading>
    <section>
      <num>2011</num>
      <heading>Size of Commissions.</heading>
      <text>Unless otherwise provided by law, each Commission shall be comprised of a minimum of three (3) and no more than five (5) Commissioners with a majority of Commissioners being a citizen of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2012</num>
      <heading>Qualifications of Commissioners.</heading>
      <text>To be eligible to serve as a Commissioner, an individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>must be eighteen (18) years of age;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>shall not have an interest in any company or business that would be subject to regulation by the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>shall not be a member of the Council or a Constitutional Officer of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2013</num>
      <heading>Appointment of Commissioners.</heading>
      <text>Commissioners shall be appointed by the Chief of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe to serve in two (2) year terms.  A Commissioner's term shall not begin until their appointment is confirmed by a majority vote of the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2014</num>
      <heading>Removal of Commissioners by Chief.</heading>
      <text>Unless otherwise provided by law, or any contractual agreements between a Commissioner and the Chief, any Commissioner may be removed by the Chief at their discretion.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2015</num>
      <heading>Removal of Commissioners by Council.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>Grounds for Removal.</heading>
        <text>Unless otherwise provided by law, the Council may remove a Commissioner from their position of Commissioner on the following grounds:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Malfeasance, misfeasance, or nonfeasance of office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>conviction by any court of any crime involving moral turpitude; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>any other grounds as established by Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>Process.</heading>
        <text>Unless a different law provides otherwise, the process for the removal of a Commissioner by the Council shall be as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>the Council may recommend removal of a Commissioner from their position as Commissioner through passage of an official resolution setting forth the grounds for removal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>the Council, after passage of the resolution outlined in subsection (a) of this Section, shall set a hearing date to consider the removal of the Commissioner and notify the alleged Commissioner in writing by certified mail, return receipt requested.  The hearing shall occur no more than ninety (90) days after passage of the resolution outlined in subsection (a) of this Section, and the hearing notice shall occur no less than thirty (30) days before the hearing date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>at the hearing, the alleged Commissioner shall have the right to protest the removal and defend the allegations against them, including the right to cross-examine any witnesses who testify against them, and shall have the right to be represented by an attorney or other advocate licensed to practice law before the Upper Mattaponi Tribe's courts; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>after the presentation of evidence at the hearing, the Council may remove the Commissioner from their position as Commissioner upon a majority vote.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2016</num>
      <heading>Officers of Commissions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>General.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Each Commission shall elect officers by majority vote: a Chairman, Vice-Chairman, and Secretary, to serve as Officers of the Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Nothing in this section limits the ability of a Commission to establish additional Officers for the Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>No Commissioner may hold more than one Office in a Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Each Officer's term shall expire on the first day of January of the year following their election.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Any Officer may resign at any time without resigning from their position as a Commissioner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>A Commissioner may be removed from their role as an Officer pursuant to a majority vote of the Commissioners.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Any Officer vacancy shall be replaced by majority vote of the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>Duties of Officers.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <heading>Annual Report.</heading>
          <text>The Officers of the Commission shall be responsible for providing an Annual Report of the Commission's activities to the Chief and the Council by the first day of January of each year covering the activities of the prior year.  The report should explain the finances of the Commission, identify any current or future liabilities, and any other material required by Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Chairman shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>preside over all meetings of the Commission;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>decide the agenda of meetings of the Commission; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>prudently preserve and faithfully execute the powers and duties of the Commission.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Vice-Chairman shall, in the absence of the Chairman, faithfully perform the powers and duties of the Chairman.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The Secretary shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>serve as custodian and historian of the Commission's records, including the keeping of appropriate meeting minutes for meetings of the Commission;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>keep the seal of the Commission and ensure that use of the seal is authorized by the Commission and affixed to all documents, advertisements, promotions, and signage on behalf of the Commission; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>keep a current register of the mailing address, phone number, and electronic mail address of each Commissioner.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2017</num>
      <heading>Employees of Commissions.</heading>
      <text>Commissions shall have the power and authority to employ such persons as may be necessary and proper for carrying out the purposes of the Commissions, subject to all applicable tribal employment laws and policies, and in accordance with the funds allocated to the Commission by the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <subheading>Subchapter C: Meetings Of Commissions</subheading>
    <section>
      <num>2021</num>
      <heading>Quorum.</heading>
      <text>At any meeting of the Commission, a majority of Commissioners shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of official business, and the act of a majority of Commissioners present at any meeting at which there is a quorum shall be an official act of the Commission.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2022</num>
      <heading>Regular Commission Meetings.</heading>
      <text>Regular meetings of the Commission shall be held, at a minimum, quarterly to conduct official business of the Commission.  Notice and agenda for a regular meeting shall be given at least forty-eight (48) hours in advance by posting on the Commission's webpage and providing a copy to the Chief and the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2023</num>
      <heading>Emergency Meetings.</heading>
      <text>Emergency meetings of a Commission may be called by the Chairman or at the request of a majority of the Commissioners.  Emergency meetings may only be called to address time-sensitive matters, to prevent injuries to persons, or to prevent injuries to personal or real property, where time requirements for public notice would make such procedure impractical and increase the likelihood of injury or damage or immediate financial loss.  Notice and agenda for an emergency meeting shall be given at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance by posting on the Commission's webpage and by electronic mail to Commissioners at the addresses on file with the Secretary and providing a copy to the Chief and the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2024</num>
      <heading>Meetings Open to Citizens.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>All meetings of a Commission, regular and emergency, shall be held at specified times and places which are convenient to the citizens of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, and shall be open to said citizens, except as hereinafter specified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In all meetings of a Commission, the vote of each Commissioner shall be publicly cast and recorded.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2025</num>
      <heading>Executive Sessions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A Commission may only enter into Executive Session for the following purposes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>discussing the employment, hiring, appointment, promotion, demotion, disciplining or resignation of any officer or employee of the Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>discussing negotiations concerning employees and representatives of employee groups;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>discussing the purchase or appraisal of real property;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>confidential communications between a Commission and its attorney concerning a pending investigation, claim, or action if the Commission, with the advice of the attorney, determines that disclosure will seriously impair the ability of the Commission to process the claim or conduct a pending investigation, litigation, or proceeding in the public interest;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>discussing any matter where disclosure of information would violate confidentiality requirements of tribal or federal law; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>discussing matters of public safety or the security of Commission records.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>An executive session for the purpose of discussing the purchase or appraisal of real property shall be limited to Commissioners, the attorney for the Commission, and the immediate staff of the Commission.  No landowner, real estate spokesperson, broker, developer, or any other person who may profit directly or indirectly by a proposed transaction concerning real property which is under consideration may be present or participate in the executive session.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>To enter executive session, the Commission must strictly comply with the following procedures:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The proposed executive session is noted on the meeting agenda;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The executive session is authorized by a majority vote of a quorum of Commissioners present and the vote is a recorded vote; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Any vote or action on any item of business considered in executive session shall be taken after the closing of executive session in the public meeting with the vote of each member publicly cast and recorded.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <subheading>Subchapter D: Finances Of Commissions</subheading>
    <section>
      <num>2031</num>
      <heading>Salaries of Commissioners.</heading>
      <text>The salaries and compensation of Commissioners, if any, shall be fixed by the Council in the annual budget and shall be paid out in like manner as other salaries and compensation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2032</num>
      <heading>Employees of Commissions.</heading>
      <text>The salaries and compensation of Commission employees shall be fixed by the Council in the annual budget and shall be paid out in like manner as other salaries and compensation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2033</num>
      <heading>Authority to Contract.</heading>
      <text>Commissions shall have the authority to enter into contracts and make guarantees in accordance with the funds allocated to the Commission by the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2034</num>
      <heading>Sovereign Immunity.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe is a sovereign Indian Nation that is immune from suit.  Nothing in this Act waives or impairs the Upper Mattaponi Tribe's immunity from suit.  As an instrumentality of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, Commissions also enjoy immunity from suit except as expressly provided in Upper Mattaponi Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Commissions shall not have the authority to waive or otherwise impair the sovereign immunity of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.  The sovereign immunity of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe may only be waived, or otherwise impaired, pursuant to the provisions of <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="XIII">Article XIII of the Constitution</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <annotation app="2026-05-22" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-12" eff="2026-05-22" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>21</num>
    <heading>The Executive, Legislative, and Judicial Branches Contracting Authority Act</heading>
    <section>
      <num>2100</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="4|21">This chapter</cite> shall be known as, the "THE EXECUTIVE, LEGISLATIVE, AND JUDICIAL BRANCHES CONTRACTING AUTHORITY ACT OF 2023 ("Act").</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-05" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2101</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="4|21">this chapter</cite> is to authorize each branch of government to contract for services and supplies in accordance with funds appropriated for such purposes in an approved budget.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-05" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2102</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>On July 22, 2023, the citizens of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe") overwhelmingly voted to adopt a new constitution ("<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>") to assert the Tribe's sovereign authority as a federally-recognized Indian tribe; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite> vests the Council with the authority to enact laws and budget resolutions; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The Executive, Legislative, and Judicial branches of government find it necessary to enter into contracts from time to time for services and supplies for their respective branches in order to fulfill their duties and responsibilities; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The Legislature finds the need to authorize officials from each branch of government to enter into contracts that are authorized by law in accordance with funds appropriated for such purposes within an approved budget.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-05" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2103</num>
      <heading>Executive Branch Authorization to Contract</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Chief and executive branch personnel shall not have the power to enter into contracts on behalf of the Tribe unless authorized to do so by law enacted by the Legislature or as otherwise authorized by <cite path="4|21">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The contracting process for the Tribe to enter into any contract shall include the following steps in the following order: (1) authorization to contract in a law enacted by the Council including <cite path="4|21">this chapter</cite>, or by decision of the Council including Department and program enabling laws; (2) selection of the vendor or contracting party pursuant to procurement policies, and negotiation and execution of the contract by the Chief or an authorized designee; (3) ratification of the contract by the Council, but only when the authorizing law expressly reserves the power to the Council to ratify the contract.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Upon authorization in a law or by <cite path="4|21">this chapter</cite>, the Chief, and executive branch personnel and subdivisions authorized by the Chief, shall have the power to select the vendor or contracting party in accordance with applicable procurement laws and policies, negotiate the contract terms with the vendor or contracting party, and enter into a contract with the vendor or contracting party on behalf of the Tribe subject to any limitations or conditions placed on the executive branch in the authorizing law including but not limited to the power of the Council to require ratification of a contract by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The Chief and executive branch personnel are hereby authorized to enter into routine contracts that are necessary for the Office of Chairman, a Department, or a program to carry out its duties and responsibilities; provided, that contacts over seven-hundred fifty thousand dollars ($750,000) shall be subject to ratification by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Any expenditure of funds by the executive branch of government shall be done in accordance with the available funds appropriated in an approved budget in accordance with the requirements of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-05" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-07-28" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2025-01" eff="2025-07-28" path="" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2104</num>
      <heading>Legislative Branch Authorization to Contract</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Council hereby authorizes the Speaker of the Legislature, on behalf of the Council, to enter into contracts, as previously and specifically authorized by the Council by Legislative Rule, to hire employees, professional advisors, consultants, and others to assist the Council and individual Representatives with fulfilling their duties to enact laws and prepare budget resolutions for the benefit of the citizens of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Speaker of the Council shall have the authority to enter into contracts for supplies or services for the Council as specifically authorized by Legislative Rule passed by the Council, subject to an appropriation of funds in an approved budget for such purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The services provided under any services contract entered into by the Council shall be limited to the exclusive benefit and use of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Any contract entered into on behalf of the Council shall include a provision stating that such contract may be canceled at any time and for any reason by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-05" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2105</num>
      <heading>Judicial Branch Authorization to Contract</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Council hereby authorizes the Chief Justice of the High Court, on behalf of the Judicial branch of government, to enter into contracts to hire professional advisors, consultants, and others to assist the courts with fulfilling their duties to the citizens of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Chief Justice shall have the authority to enter into contracts for supplies or services for the courts, subject to an appropriation of funds in an approved budget for such purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The services provided under any services contract entered into by the Chief Justice shall be limited to the exclusive benefit and use of the courts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Any contract entered into on behalf of the Judicial branch shall include a provision stating that such contract may be canceled at any time and for any reason by the Chief Justice.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-05" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
