<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribal Code of Law">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>42</num>
  <heading>Tribal Land, Buildings, Property, and Works</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>1</num>
    <heading>The Sharon Indian School Foundation, Inc. Reorganization Act of 2024</heading>
    <section>
      <num>100</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as, the "The Sharon Indian School Foundation, Inc. Reorganization Act of 2024" ("Act").</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-28" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-02" eff="2024-02-28" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>101</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to authorize and direct the reorganization of the Sharon Indian School Foundation, Inc. ("SISF") including the selection of a Board of Directors, an update of the Articles of Incorporation, and the development of corporate Bylaws, in accordance with the corporate articles for the benefit of the citizens of the Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-28" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-02" eff="2024-02-28" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>102</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>On June 14, 1976, upon the approval of the Articles of Incorporation ("Articles"), the <em>Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribal Association, Inc. </em>was incorporated under Virginia state law as a non-stock (non-profit) corporation (the "Tribal Association") for the benefit of the Upper Mattaponi People.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>In April 2016, the People created the "<em>Constitution and By-Laws of the Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe</em>", which acted as a corporation known as the <em>Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe, Inc.</em>, a non-profit corporation organized under the laws of the Commonwealth of Virginia, in conjunction with the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>On January 9, 2018, the United States officially recognized the Upper Mattaponi Tribe when it enacted the Thomasina E. Jordan Indian Tribes of Virginia Federal Recognition Act of 2017.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>On October 8, 2020, the <em>Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe, Inc.</em> was renamed as the "<em>Sharon Indian School Foundation, Inc.</em>" ("SISF" or "Foundation"), which became the successor corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>On July 22, 2023, the voters approved the new <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> ("<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">New Constitution</cite>"). The <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">New Constitution</cite> expressly replaced the 2016 Constitution and By-Laws.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>The Board of Directors of the Foundation consists of five Members, whose terms of office as Board Members coincided with the terms of office of officials of the Tribe, which were altered and reset as a result of the approval of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">New Constitution</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>The Council has identified the need to clarify the qualifications, requirements, terms of office, and process to select and install Board Members of the Foundation, and to direct the development of a formal process to address Board Member vacancies in the future.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>The Articles are silent on the issue of the expiration of Board Members' terms of office or the process to fill any Board Member vacancies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(I)</num>
        <text>The 2023 Annual Report of the Foundation ("Annual Report") filed with the State Corporation Commission listed five Directors and officers.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-28" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-02" eff="2024-02-28" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>103</num>
      <heading>Board of Directors of the Foundation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Council hereby authorizes and directs the five Directors and officers listed in the 2023 Annual Report and who are still serving on the Board of Directors to officially modify the Articles of the Foundation to set new requirements for including: (1) at least three Board Members with all Members serving four-year, staggered terms of office; (2) Board Members selected upon appointment by the Chief and confirmation by the Council; and, (3) Board Member vacancies filled upon nomination by the Chief and confirmation by the Council.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The initial terms of office for Board Members shall begin upon the approval of the modified Articles of the Foundation and the installation of a newly seated Board of Directors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Articles of the Foundation shall include a requirement that a majority of the Members of the Board of Directors must be citizens of the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Council hereby authorizes and directs the five Directors and officers listed in the 2023 Annual Report and who are still serving on the Board of Directors to officially adopt Bylaws for the Foundation.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-28" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-02" eff="2024-02-28" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>2</num>
    <heading>Land Financing Act of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</heading>
    <section>
      <num>200</num>
      <heading>Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="42|2">This chapter</cite> shall be known as the "Land Financing Act of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe."</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|I|1-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>201</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text><cite path="42|2">This chapter</cite> is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (also referred to herein as "Tribe") and pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>, which confers all Legislative power of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe in the Council of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|I|1-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>202</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text><cite path="42|2">This chapter</cite> is enacted to authorize the Chief or his designee to obtain financing for the purchase of land.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|I|1-3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>203</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="42|2">this chapter</cite> shall be effective upon the date signed by the Chief of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, or upon the date of a veto override by the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|I|1-4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>204</num>
      <heading>Interpretation</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="42|2">this chapter</cite> shall be interpreted to be in accordance with tribal customary law. Whenever there is uncertainty or a question as to the interpretation of certain provisions of <cite path="42|2">this chapter</cite>, tribal law and custom shall be controlling, and where appropriate, may be based on the written or oral testimony of a qualified tribal elder, tribal historian, or tribal representative. If the traditions and customs of the Tribe are inconclusive in any matter, the Court shall construe it consistently with applicable textual tribal law. In the absence of applicable tribal customary law or textual tribal law, the Court shall construe it consistently with applicable law of other jurisdictions.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|I|1-5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>205</num>
      <heading>Severability and non-liability</heading>
      <text>If any section, provision, or portion of <cite path="42|2">this chapter</cite> is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of <cite path="42|2">this chapter</cite> shall not be affected thereby.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|I|1-7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>206</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Purchase of Land. Within budgetary constraints, the Chief is hereby authorized to purchase land within five miles of the current tribal headquarters in King William.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Line of Credit. The Chief or his designee is authorized to obtain a line of credit which may be used to finance the acquisition of land.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Waiver of Immunity. If necessary, the Chief is authorized to pledge as collateral for securing such line of credit, and the Chief is authorized to waive the sovereign immunity of the Tribe up to the amount of the line of credit and as it relates to the collateral specified above, for solely the purpose of ensuring the repayment of the line of credit.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|II|2-1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>207</num>
      <heading>Reporting</heading>
      <text>The Chief shall report each month to the Council on the amount drawn or repaid under the line of credit, and what land, if any has been purchased since the last report.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-02-07" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-01" eff="2024-02-07" path="attachments|law|II|2-2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3</num>
    <heading>Trust Land Acquisition Statute of 2024</heading>
    <section>
      <num>300</num>
      <heading>Title</heading>
      <text>This Code shall be known as the "Trust Land Acquisition Statute of 2024"</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>301</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text>This Code is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (also referred to herein as "Tribe") and pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>, which confers all Legislative power of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe in the Council of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>302</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="42|3">this chapter</cite> is to authorize and direct the Chief to acquire additional lands for housing and economic development purposes for the benefit of the Tribe and the People.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>303</num>
      <heading>Effective Date</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this code shall be effective upon the date signed by the Chief of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, or upon the date of a veto override by the Council.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>304</num>
      <heading>Interpretation</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this Code shall be interpreted to be in accordance with tribal customary law. Whenever there is uncertainty or a question as to the interpretation of certain provisions of this Code, tribal law and custom shall be controlling, and where appropriate, may be based on the written or oral testimony of a qualified tribal elder, tribal historian, or tribal representative. If the traditions and customs of the Tribe are inconclusive in any matter, the Court shall construe it consistently with applicable textual tribal law. In the absence of applicable tribal customary law or textual tribal law, the Court shall construe it consistently with applicable federal or state law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>305</num>
      <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
      <text>If any section, provision, or portion of this Code is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this Code shall not be affected thereby.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>306</num>
      <heading>Authorization to Purchase</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby authorizes the Chief or his designee or a Tribally Owned Corporation to purchase or acquire land subject to appropriation for such purposes.  In making such appropriations, the Council may make restrictions on the total amount expended for a particular tract of land, including price per acre limitations on the amount expended. In the process of purchasing such land, an attorney must be consulted, and before the land can be purchased the attorney shall state in writing to the Council and the Chairman that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Title to be conveyed to the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is sufficient to satisfy the United States in an action under 25 U.S.C. part 151;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>a phase 1 environmental review reveals no impairments to the land to be purchased; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>the other requirements of 25 U.S.C. part 151 likely can be met when the Upper Mattaponi Tribe seeks to put the land into trust.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|8" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>307</num>
      <heading>Duty to Apply for Trust Status</heading>
      <text>Within 180 days of acquiring title of property purchased under <cite path="42|3">this chapter</cite>, the Chief or his designee shall take the necessary steps to take the land into trust.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-04-29" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-01" eff="2024-04-29" path="attachments|law|9" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>4</num>
    <heading>Tribal Land Permitting Act of 2025</heading>
    <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
    <section>
      <num>400</num>
      <text>This law shall be known as the "Tribal Land Permitting Act of 2025."</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>401</num>
      <text>Pursuant to the requirements and limits of this law, and upon the issuance of a permit, the Tribe shall make its lands available to others for organized gatherings</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>402</num>
      <text>The Tribe's lands may not be permitted to be used for political purposes, except the Tribe's own elections or any polling the Tribe may conduct for local, state or federal elections</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>403</num>
      <text>The Chief shall maintain a list of those lands which may be made available for use by others and those lands which shall not be made available for use by others.  If land is categorized as not available for use by others, it may not be used other than by the Tribe for either organized or incidental uses</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>404</num>
      <text>Except those lands the Chief identifies as not available for use, Tribe's lands shall be open to all citizens of the Tribe and their guests for incidental use (walking, jogging, picnicking, etc.) without need for a permit.  Such incidental use shall be limited to transient use for less than 12 hours and shall not permit any camping or overnight stays</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>405</num>
      <text>An organized use requiring a permit shall be all uses other than incidental uses.  Examples of organized uses requiring a permit include, without limitation: weddings, family reunions, ceremonies, or sporting events</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>406</num>
      <text>The Chief shall establish and annually revise a "Facilities Use Request Form."  The Chief shall establish and annually revise a fee schedule for the application to use the Tribe's lands.  The fee may vary based on the land to be used, the type of use, or the intended number of participants</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>407</num>
      <text>Upon approval of a completed "Facilities Use Request Form," payment of the relevant fee and issuance of a permit, any person may use the Tribe's lands for organized uses</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|8" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>408</num>
      <text>Before any person or entity may obtain a permit to use any of the Tribe's lands, they shall submit a completed "Facilities Use Request Form" and any relevant application fee.  The Facilities Use Request Form shall be submitted to the Chief's office in writing, and shall be signed and dated</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|9" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>409</num>
      <text>The Chief shall review each submitted Facilities Use Request Form and shall determine if the form is complete.  To be complete, all needed information must be supplied, and the application fee must be paid in full.  If it is not complete, or the fee is not paid, the Facilities Use Request Form shall be returned to the applicant, indicating what is needed for completeness</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|10" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>410</num>
      <text>When the Chief decides a submitted Facilities Use Request Form is complete, he shall   decide whether to issue the permit based on whether the use requested is consistent with the Tribe's policies, whether the requested use of the land would interfere with the Tribe's other uses of that land or other lands, whether in his opinion the use should not be permitted to maintain the proper administration of the Tribe or its lands, the total amount of land available and the amount of land needed for the use, any special conditions for trust or restricted lands, the historical or cultural importance of the land to be used, the condition of the natural environment and the potential impact of the use, any past or future uses of the land which may impact the requested use, and any other factor which the chief deems important</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|11" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>411</num>
      <text>  Before any use of the land may occur, the Chief shall issue a written permit.  The permit may be revoked at any time by the Chief for any reason he deems reasonable</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|12" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>412</num>
      <text>The granting of a use permit does not create any right, title or interest in the land.  A use permit is not a lease.  It is a permission which may be revoked at any time</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|13" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>413</num>
      <text>Tribal citizens shall not pay a fee for the permitted use of the Tribe's land</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|14" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>414</num>
      <text>If the entity seeking to use the Tribe's land is a non-profit organization, the Chief may elect to waive the fee</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|15" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>415</num>
      <text>If the use of tribal land shall primarily involve children (e.g., scouting or sports), the Chief shall ensure that the person obtains a liability waiver from the parent of each child and submits to the Chief each liability waiver for each child before that child is provided entry onto the Tribe's land</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|16" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>416</num>
      <text>The Chief shall maintain insurance on its lands to ensure that any person injured while using the Tribe's lands may make a claim on that insurance.  This shall not constitute a waiver of the Tribe's and its officers and employee's immunity from suit</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|17" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>417</num>
      <text>Where the Chief deems it appropriate he may require any person or entity seeking a use permit to obtain liability insurance to insure against injury to any person entering the Tribe's land under a use permit.  Where the use primarily involves children (e.g., scouting or sports), the Chief must ensure such liability insurance has been issued, that it is current, and that the Tribe is listed as an additional insured on the policy before the permit may be issued</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|18" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>418</num>
      <text>No person using the Tribe's lands may cause a nuisance, nor may he damage or deface the Tribe's property.  If a nuisance is caused during a permitted use, or damage is caused to the Tribe's property, then the person permitted to use the land shall not be permitted to use any Tribal land for one (1) year, and they shall be liable for any damages caused.  In addition, the persons who caused the nuisance or damage, if they were not the ones permitted directly to use the land shall not be permitted to use any Tribal land for one (1) year, and they shall be liable for any damages caused</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|19" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>419</num>
      <text>Where the term Chief is used herein it means the Chief or his designee</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>420</num>
      <text>Nothing herein shall be used to permit hunting or fishing</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|21" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>421</num>
      <text>All fires on Tribal land must be contained in an enclosed structure, such as a fire ring or pit. Open fires are prohibited. Permit holders must ensure that proper fire safety measures are in place, including having a means to extinguish the fire and ensuring it is fully extinguished before leaving. Non-compliance will result in the revocation of the permit and a one (1) year ban from using Tribal land, along with liability for any damages caused</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="" type="History"/>
        <annotation app="2025-03-19" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-02" eff="2025-03-19" path="attachments|law|22" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
