<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribal Code of Law">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>47</num>
  <heading>Tribal Health and Welfare</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>1</num>
    <heading>Department of Health Enabling Act</heading>
    <section>
      <num>101</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="47|1">This chapter</cite> shall be known as the Department of Health Enabling Act ("Act").</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-007" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|101" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>102</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="47|1">this chapter</cite> is to establish the Department of Health.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-007" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|102" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>103</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>reorganizing the structure of governmental departments and programs in accordance with the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite> will promote efficiency within the Tribe; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>establishing a Department of Health within the executive branch of government will assist the Tribe in managing, administering, and evaluating various health care programs for the benefit of citizens of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-007" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|103" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>104</num>
      <heading>Organization of the Department of Health</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall have the authority to organize and operate the Department of Health in an efficient and fiscally sound manner in accordance with the size, scope, and funding of the various programs, services, and other activities that are assigned to the Department of Health from time to time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Department of Health may include the following programs, services, and activities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Primary Care Medical Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Dental Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Behavioral and Mental Health Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Public Health Nursing and Other Services</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Administration</em>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Any other program or service established by the Chief, subject to ratification by the Council.</em>
          </text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-007" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|104" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>105</num>
      <heading>Department of Health Goals and Objectives</heading>
      <text>The mission of the Department of Health is to assess and implement various health care programs of the Tribe in a well-coordinated and collaborative manner that will enhance educational awareness, disease prevention, and healthy behavioral changes. The primary goal of the Department of Health is to provide comprehensive health care awareness that will target multiple dimensions of health such as physical, mental, emotional, and social needs of citizens of the Tribe of all ages.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-007" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|105" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>106</num>
      <heading>Authority to Operate and Administer the Department of Health</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Chief, and any person(s) designated by the Chief and working at the direction of the Chief, shall have the authority to operate and manage the Department of Health and/or any portion or component of the Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Chief, and any person(s) designated by the Chief and working at the direction of the Chief, shall have the authority to administer the authorized funds appropriated for the Department of Health or its subdivisions,</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>NOTES:</strong>
      </text>
      <text>
        <strong>Primary Care Medical Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of primary healthcare services, appropriate for a local medical center to prevent and treat disease and injury and to promote improvements in health status and outcomes. All medical services, treatments, and laboratory services provided to pediatric and adult patients include the coordination of referrals to outside services not available at the clinic. Primary Care Medical Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Family Health Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Diabetes Treatment and Prevention services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Laboratory Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Pharmaceutical Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Telemedicine Services 6. Eldercare Services</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Dental Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of dental services, appropriate for a local dental center to prevent and treat disease and promote improvements in dental health. All dental services, treatment, and laboratory services provided to pediatric and adult patients include the coordination of referrals to outside service not available at the dental clinic. Dental Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Preventive Care - Checkups, Cleaning and Deep Cleaning</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Restorative Services - Fillings, Crowns and Bridges</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Dentures</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Pediatric</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Behavioral Health and Mental Health Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of behavioral and mental health services, appropriate for our citizens, local school systems, and community at-large. All services and treatments provided to pediatric and adult patients include the coordination of referrals to outside services not available through the Tribe. Behavioral and Mental Health Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Individual and Family Support Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Mental Health Services</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Public Health Nursing and Other Services</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of home and community-based services, appropriate for ensuring the health and well-being of our citizens and community at-large. Public Health Nursing and Other Services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Health, Education, Health Promotion, and Disease Prevention</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Public Health Nursing</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Physical Therapy 4. Occupational Therapy</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Nutrition and Dietetics</text>
      </para>
      <text>
        <strong>Administration</strong>
      </text>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Comprehensive Health Program provides a comprehensive range of administrative services, appropriate for the operation of the Health program. All administrative services not provided by Tribal employees will be contracted with outside vendors where appropriate. Administrative services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>General Administrative Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Business Office</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Housekeeping Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Human Resources</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Infection Control Services</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Information Technology</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>Medical Records</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>Medical Services Administration</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9.</num>
        <text>Patient Registration</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-007" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|106" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>2</num>
    <heading>Department of Health Procurement Policy Authorization Act</heading>
    <section>
      <num>201</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="47|2">This chapter</cite> shall be known as the Department of Health Procurement Policy Authorization Act ("Act").</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-008" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|101" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>202</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="47|2">this chapter</cite> is to authorize and establish a Procurement Policy for the Department of Health.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-008" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|102" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>203</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In accordance with the authority under the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>, the Council established a Department of Health to operate and administer various health care programs and services for the Tribe; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Department of Health and programs operating within the Department of Health have grown significantly in a short period of time, and the Tribe's procurement policies can no longer efficiently accommodate the unique needs of the Department of Health to obtain and administer large programs and budgets, including the need to purchase expensive medical equipment; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>based on the success of the Tribe's existing health care programs and services, the Council finds the need to authorize a separate procurement policy for the Department of Health, subject to modification by the Chief as authorized by law.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-008" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|103" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>204</num>
      <heading>Procurement Policy</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall have the authority to establish and modify a written procurement policy for the Department of Health and/or its subdivisions. Any modification to an existing procurement policy for the Department of Health shall be provided to the Council within thirty days of approval by the Chief.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any procurement policy for the Department of Health approved by the Chief shall include the following provisions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any other procurement policy or resolution adopted by the Tribe, the Department of Health is authorized to negotiate, execute and otherwise conclude, and administer contracts and agreements in accordance with appropriated funds as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text><u>Operational Contracts</u>: for goods and services, including those with state and federal agencies ("intergovernmental agreements"), that are necessary to maintain operations, services, and to comply with Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services ("CMS") conditions of participation (collectively, "Operational Contracts"); and,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text><u>Revenue Contracts</u>: with insurance providers, third-party administrators, and other similar type of patient benefit providers that are necessary for the Department of Health to submit claims and receive payment for services (collectively, "Revenue Contracts").</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's liability for an Operational Contract or Revenue Contract entered pursuant to this Act shall not exceed, and sovereign immunity is not waived for, an amount greater than the Tribe's applicable insurance coverage or the total value of the contract, whichever is lower; provided, that the Department of Health shall provide the Council and Chief with an annual written report detailing the number of contracts entered into that included a waiver of sovereign immunity including the purposes and terms of each waiver.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>On a semi-annual basis, the Department of Health shall provide a summary of all current Operational and Revenue Contracts, which shall include a description of the type of services provided under the contract, the total and annual amount of the contract, the duration of the contract, and a current revenue and expenditure report, to the Chief and Council.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-09-21" doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-008" eff="2023-09-21" path="attachments|law|104" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
