<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Order No. 2025-01">
  <num>2025-01</num>
  <heading>Secretary Pro Tem Appointment</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-04-26</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-04-26</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-01.pdf">Order. No. 2025-01</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council held this 26th day of April, 2025, the following Order was adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>On July 22, 2023, the citizens of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe") voted to adopt a new constitution ("Constitution") to assert the Tribe's sovereign authority as an Indian Tribe, and to confirm and to reorganize the Tribe to exercise its full governmental authority in a fair and equitable manner; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Council of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Council") is vested with the authority to pass Legislative Rules and govern its internal administrative and operational matters and to establish legislative procedures pursuant to Article VII, Sections 4(h) and 6 of the Constitution. Such Orders, as these, are not subject to consideration by the Chief, and become effective on the date set forth above; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>it is necessary for the efficient operation of the Tribe's affairs that all meetings are conducted and official documents are signed without interruption; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the position of the Secretary is critical to these functions; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in the event of the absence of the Secretary, it is essential that the duties of the Secretary continue to be carried out seamlessly;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED:</conjunction>
      <text>In the absence of the Secretary, the Speaker of the Council is hereby authorized to designate a qualified individual to serve as Secretary Pro Tem.</text>
      <text>The individual designated as Secretary Pro Tem shall have the authority to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>Preside over roll call and record votes in the absence of the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>II.</num>
        <text>Sign official documents, including resolutions, ordinances, and other necessary paperwork, on behalf of the Secretary until the Secretary returns.</text>
      </para>
      <text>The appointment of the Secretary Pro Tem shall remain in effect until the Secretary returns or a new designation is made by the Speaker.</text>
      <text>The Speaker shall inform the Council of the designation of the Secretary Pro Tem as soon as practicable, and the appointment shall be recorded in the meeting minutes.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that this Resolution shall take effect immediately upon adoption.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Order was duly voted upon by the Council on the 26th day of April, 2025, at a General Meeting with a vote of <u>6</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>1</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
