<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-09">
  <num>2024-09</num>
  <heading>Appointment of the Board of Directors to UMIT Technologies, LLC</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-06-25</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-06-22</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-09.pdf">Res. No. 2024-09</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>At a duly called Regular Meeting of the Council held this 22 day of June, 2024, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council ("Council") is vested with the authority to enact laws and Budget Resolutions pursuant to Article VII, Section 4(a) of the Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Constitution"); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council formed Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC as a Tribally Owned Limited Liability Company pursuant to the Upper Mattaponi Limited Liability Code; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in Section 10 of the Operating Agreement for Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC, Tribal Council delegated the management of the Company and all business affairs to a set of Board of Directors; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council hereby sets the number of seats on the Board of Directors for Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC to three (3); and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjucntion>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED</conjucntion>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council hereby appoints the following to serve as the Board of Directors for Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC:</text>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Joseph C. Adams</strong>
      </text>
      <text class="center">12317 Maybrook Lane</text>
      <text class="center">Glen Allen, VA 23059</text>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Steven M. Tupponce</strong>
      </text>
      <text class="center">309 Tyler Trail</text>
      <text class="center">Aylett, VA 23009</text>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Deborah P. Wilkinson</strong>
      </text>
      <text class="center">9606 Torno Drive</text>
      <text class="center">Glen Allen, VA 23060</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 22 day of June, 2024, at a Regular Meeting with a vote of <u>5</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>2</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Constitution of the Tribe.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
