<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-17">
  <num>2024-17</num>
  <heading>Federal Corporate Charter for UMT Holdings</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-10-26</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-10-26</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-17.pdf">Res. No. 2024-17</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>
      <em>October 26, 2024</em>
    </strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>FEDERAL CHARTER OF INCORPORATION</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>issued by</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>BUREAU OF INDIAN AFFAIRS</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>to the</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>
      <em>Upper Mattaponi Tribe</em>
    </strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>for</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>UMT Holdings</strong>
  </text>
  <text class="center">A Federally Chartered Corporation</text>
  <text class="center">************************</text>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>RECITALS</strong>
  </text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Congress of the United States has enacted the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, as amended, 25 U.S.C. 461 et seq., which, in Section 17 thereof (25 U.S.C. § 477), authorizes the Secretary of the Interior to issue a federal corporate charter to an Indian Tribe; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (herein the "Tribe") is a federally recognized Indian Tribe and is consequently recognized by the Internal Revenue Service as an Indian Tribal Government under the Tribal Governmental Tax Status Act (26 U.S.C. § 7871 et seq.).</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Council (herein the "Council") is the governing body of the Tribe; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on ________, 2024 the Council petitioned the Secretary of the Interior to issue a federal charter of incorporation to the Tribe to establish a business corporation as authorized by Section 17 of the Indian Reorganization Act; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council has found that the formation of UMT Holdings (the "Corporation") pursuant to a section 17 Charter will serve the best interests of the Tribe, its members and its enterprises and will protect the political integrity, economic security and health and welfare of the Tribe and its members by, among other things: 1) creating a legal structure which provides for the segregation of Tribe governmental assets and liabilities from Tribe business assets and liabilities, and 2) creating a legal structure which provides for the segregation of discrete Corporation assets and liabilities into separate Corporation subdivisions, without divesting either the Corporation or the Tribe of the privileges and immunities arising pursuant to their legal status under federal and Tribal law; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Constitution does not include an impairment of contracts clause and the Tribe desires, by and through the Section 17 Charter of the Corporation, to provide assurance to business associates that the Corporation may enter into contracts without the Tribe subsequently enacting laws materially impairing such contracts other than as necessary to protect health or safety within the jurisdiction of the Tribe; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the terms and provisions of this Charter were approved by the Council on _______________ pursuant to ________; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>all of the legal prerequisites to the issuance of this Charter have been fulfilled;</text>
      <text><strong>NOW, THEREFORE</strong>, I, Kimberly Bouchard, Eastern Regional Director, Bureau of Indian Affairs, by virtue of the power conferred upon the Secretary of the Interior by the said Act and delegated to me, do hereby issue this Charter of Incorporation to the Tribe for UMT Holdings, to be operative when ratified by the governing body of the Tribe.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe on the 26 day of October, 2024, at a Regular Meeting with a vote of  ____6_____ in favor and ____0_____ opposed, _____1____ abstaining, and ____0_____ absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
    <text>__________________________________</text>
    <text>
      <em>Secretary of the Council or Designee</em>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
