<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-03">
  <num>2024-03</num>
  <heading>Upper Mattaponi Seal Act</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-04-29</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-04-27</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-03.pdf">Res. No. 2024-03</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>At a duly called Meeting of the Council held this 27<sup>th</sup> day of April, 2024, the following resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the Council of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe") is a recognized sovereign indigenous American Indian tribal nation governed by an elected Chief and Tribal Council elected by the enrolled citizens of the Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the Preamble of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> states that the  <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite> was adopted to "sustain and promote [the Tribe's] culture, language, and way of life"; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the Seal of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is necessary to carry out the Tribe's policy, conduct its business, and provide services to its citizens; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>consistent with the duties, laws, and practices of the Tribe, the Tribal Council desires to protect the Tribe's intellectual property, especially the Seal of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, which is used for official government business; therefore, be it</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Council votes to memorialize the attached image, which has served exclusively as the official Seal of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe since March 23, 2024, to continue as the official tribal insignia and Seal of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe, for the exclusive use of the duly elected Upper Mattaponi tribal government.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Council vote to file this official Seal of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe with the United States Patent and Trademark Office's tribal insignia database to protect the Seal of the Tribe as the Tribe's intellectual property and part of its cultural heritage.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on April 27, 2024, at a Regular Meeting with a vote of 6 in favor and 0 opposed, 0 abstaining, and 0 (vacant) absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
