<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Bill No. 2024-008">
  <num>2024-008</num>
  <heading>Bill to Designate Authorized Organizational Representative for the ANA SEDS Grant</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-03-29</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-03-28</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-008.pdf">Bill No. 2024-008</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called Meeting of the Council held this <u>28</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of March 2024, the following Bill was adopted.</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (the "Tribe"), whose address is 13476 King William RD, King William, Virginia, 23086-3401, was awarded an Administration for Native Americans (ANA) Social and Economic Development Strategies (SEDS) Grant for a Tribal Project entitled Sovereign Promise: Realizing the Upper Mattaponi Future; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the ANA requires the designation of an Authorized Organizational Representative (AOR) for oversight of and communications regarding the ANA SEDS Grant,; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the current listed AOR is no longer employed by the Tribe; and</text>
      <text><strong>THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED,</strong> the Council hereby approves the designation of an AOR for the ANA SEDS grant; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council authorizes Chief W. Frank Adams to be its Authorized Organization Representative (AOR), for ANA SEDS Grant Tribal Project entitled Sovereign Promise: Realizing the Upper Mattaponi Future.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on <u>March 28</u>, 2024, at a Special Called Meeting with a vote of <u>6</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>1</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Constitution of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>Secretary of the Council</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
