<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-016">
  <num>2024-016</num>
  <heading>Authorization and Approval of Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC</heading>
  <meta>
    <stub/>
    <effective>2024-06-25</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-06-22</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-016.pdf">Res. No. 2024-016</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called Regular Meeting of the Council held this 22 day of June, 2024, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(c)">Article VII, Section 4(c)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>, the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council (the "Council") is vested with the authority to enact laws and Budget Resolution for the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (the "Tribe"); and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Upper Mattaponi Tribe Limited Liability Company Code (the "Code") requires that all limited liability companies wholly owned by the Tribe, with the Tribe as the sole owner, be created by a duly adopted resolution of the Council; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Code requires an organizer of a limited liability company to file executed Articles of Organization with the Administrator together with fees and any accompanying documents required by law; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Code provides that the Administrator is the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council or their designated representative; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Code provides that the existence of a limited liability company begins on the effective date of the Articles of Organization; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Code provides that filing is conclusive evidence that all conditions precedent required to performed under the Code are fulfilled and that a limited liability company is formed under the Code; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC has submitted to the Council</text>
      <text>its Articles of Organization and Operating Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Pursuant to the submitted Articles of Organization and Operating Agreement, Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC is wholly owned by the Tribe with the Tribe as the sole owner; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Pursuant to the submitted Articles of Organization, the effective date of Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC shall be on the date the Council enacts a resolution authorizing and approving the Articles of Organization; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Council finds it in the best interests of the Tribe to create Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby authorizes the formation of Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC, approves the attached "Articles of Organization" and "Operating Agreement" of Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 22 day of June, 2024, at a Regular Meeting with a vote of <u>5</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>2</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
