<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Ord. No. 2024-001">
  <num>2024-001</num>
  <heading>First Appointment of Officers</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-01-27</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-01-27</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-1.pdf">Ord. No. 2024-1</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called Regular Meeting of the Council held this 27<sup>th</sup> day of January 2024, the following Order was adopted.</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>On July 22, 2023, the citizens of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe") voted to adopt a new constitution ("<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>") to assert the Tribe's sovereign authority as an Indian Tribe, and to confirm and to reorganize the Tribe to exercise its full governmental authority in a fair and equitable manner; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>in order to secure the smooth functioning of the Council, it desires to appoint such officers and define such roles for such officers as the Duly Elected Members of the Council believe is needed. The Council agrees that it may, at any time, by a majority vote modify these appointments and the roles and duties of these appointments; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>The Council is vested with the power to select its own officers, including a speaker from among the representatives pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|6">Article VII, Section 6</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>. Such Orders, as these, are not subject to consideration by the Chief, and become effective on the date set forth above.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby enacts the attached order entitled, "First Appointment of Officers"; and,</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on <u>January 27</u>, 202<u>4</u> at a Regular Meeting with a vote of <u>7</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <attachment id="order">
    <heading>First Appointment of Officers</heading>
    <text>The Council, meeting on January 27, 2024 hereby establishes the following roles for the effective administration of its affairs, appoints one of its members to each role, and establishes the duties for each role:</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Council: Appointee: Rob Adams.</text>
    <text>Role of the Speaker: To do or delegate all those responsibilities set out in the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> and to serve as parliamentary leader and presiding officer of the Council. The Speaker shall also make all official statements on behalf of the Council, and if such statements impact the Tribe, shall consult with the Chief before public statements are released. The speaker shall call and send notice of all meetings of the Council, and if three or more members of the Council request a meeting the speaker shall call it at a reasonable time thereafter.</text>
    <text>Assistant Speaker of the Council: Appointee: Ken Adams</text>
    <text>Role of the Assistant Speaker: To perform the duties of the Speaker in the event the Speaker is unable to do so.</text>
    <text>Secretary of the Council: Appointee: Wilma Hicks</text>
    <text>Role of the Secretary of the Council: The secretary is the recording officer of the Council and the custodian of its records. The Secretary shall keep a register, or roll, of the members and shall call the roll when required; notify officers, committees, and delegates of their appointment, and furnish committees with all papers referred to them, and sign with the Speaker all orders as may be required. The Secretary shall also keep the official copies of all the records of the Council, including the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">constitution</cite>, rules of order, and the minutes of all meetings of the Council. The Secretary shall within a reasonable time before any council meeting, prepare the agenda for all meetings of the Council, and shall prepare the form for all enactments of the Council, including therein all the items requested by any member of the Council. In the absence of the Speaker or the Assistant Speaker, the Secretary shall perform the duties of the Speaker. The Secretary may delegate any of these duties as needed.</text>
  </attachment>
</document>
