<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-04">
  <num>2025-04</num>
  <heading>Award of Construction Bid for Right Flank Road Health Clinic</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-03-24</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-03-22</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-04.pdf">Res. No. 2025-04</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">
    <strong/>
  </text>
  <text class="center">A Resolution to accept and authorize the execution of the construction bid for the Right Flank Road Health Clinic and relocation of Home Health and Human Resources Offices.</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council held this 22 day of March, 2025, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (the "Tribe") is an Indian Tribe that has existed from time immemorial and is federally recognized on a government-to-government basis by the United States of America; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe, within the limits of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> (the "<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>") and tribal laws, has the authority to enter into contracts and procure services to meet the Tribe's growing needs and those of its citizens; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribal Code of Law" path="4|ยง1106">Chapter 11 Section 1106 (Procurement Policy)</cite> of the Tribe's Code of Law establishes a written procurement policy for the Health Department; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Health Department procurement policy requires Council approval on bids greater than $500,000.00; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the construction bids for 7501 Right Flank Road, Mechanicsville, VA exceed $500,000.00; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>ENV Architecture &amp; Design, LLC (the "Architects"), the Tribe's architectural firm, received, reviewed, and leveled three bids from three qualified contractors; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Architects recommend Emerald Construction as the general contractor for the 7501 Right Flank Road construction project based on their overall responsiveness, price, and schedule; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the approved budget for FY25 Q1 modification included $2,160,000.00 for the construction/renovation of the building and the Emerald Construction bid is $1,197,486.00;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council authorizes the bid award for the 7501 Right Flank Road construction project to Emerald Construction and grants the Chief authority to execute the construction contract in accordance with Upper Mattaponi law.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 22 day of March, 2025, at a General Meeting with a vote of  <u>7</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
