<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-09">
  <num>2025-09</num>
  <heading>Authorizing Execution of a BIA 638 Contract for Natural Resource Management and Education</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-05-05</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-05-05</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-09.pdf">Res. No. 2025-09</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution to authorize the Chief to enter into a Natural Resources Management contract with the Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA) regarding the Tribal Youth Hunting and Conservation Program.</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council held this 15<sup>th</sup> day of May, 2025, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (the "Tribe") is an Indian Tribe that has existed from time immemorial and is federally recognized on a government-to-government basis by the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(c)">Article VII, Section 4(c)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> (the "<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>"), the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council (the "Council") is vested with the authority to enact laws for the safety, health, and welfare of the Tribe; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe, as a sovereign nation, retains inherent rights to hunting, fishing, and gathering, rights that remain unaltered by treaties with the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe recognizes the necessity of maintaining oversight and regulation to prevent the depletion of fish, wildlife, plants, and other natural resources essential to its cultural and ecological heritage; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe has received a grant award from the United States regarding its Tribal Youth Initiative for a Tribal Youth Hunting and Conservation Program; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe is required to enter into a Natural Resources Management contract, pursuant to the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act, as a prerequisite of receiving the grant award; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Natural Resources Management contract will support a range of tribal programs and activities, including but not limited to, agriculture, wildlife management, conservation enforcement, invasive species control, forestry, fish hatchery operations, and water resource management; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Natural Resources Management contract will house the Tribal Youth Initiative funding for the Tribal Youth Hunting and Conservation Program, engaging tribal youth in conservation, hunting, and resource stewardship activities; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Youth Hunting and Conservation Program will generate economic benefits, protect cultural, spiritual, and traditional resources, and promote the sustainable use and preservation of the Tribe's natural resources.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>THAT the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council hereby authorizes the Chief of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe to execute a Natural Resources Management contract with the Bureau of Indian Affairs for the management, development, and protection of Indian Trust land and natural resource assets.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 15<sup>th</sup> day of May, 2025, at a General Meeting with a vote of <u>7</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
