<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-14">
  <num>2025-14</num>
  <heading>Recognition of the ICC as an Intertribal Consortium</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-11-07</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-11-06</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-14.pdf">Res. No. 2025-14</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution supporting the Upper Mattaponi Tribe's participation in the Indigenous Conservation Council (ICC) to advance intertribal efforts to rematriate and care for ancestral lands, uphold tribal sovereignty, and collaborate on conservation goals as a future signatory of the Chesapeake Bay Watershed Agreement.</text>
  <text>At a duly called Special Session of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council held this 6<sup>th</sup> day of November, 2025, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe is a federally recognized tribe located at 13476 King William Road, King William, VA 23086 that retains its inherent sovereignty and self-determination as codified through multiple treaties including the Middle Plantation Treaty of 1677 and most recently recognized by the US federal government as a legal and political entity on January 29, 2018 through the Thomasina E. Jordan Indian Tribes of Virginia Federal Recognition Act of 2017; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe agreed to support the establishment of the Indigenous Conservation Council (ICC), a 501(c)3 organization co-created by the seven federally recognized tribes to build the capacity of Tribal Nations to rematriate and care for their lands in a manner that reinforces sovereignty and self-determination; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe has appointed W. Frank Adams, Chief of the Upper Mattaponi, as a member in good standing of the ICC Board of Directors, current as of January 1, 2025; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe recognizes the ICC as an intertribal consortium that will work in concert with its Tribal Nation members and serve as a signatory of the Chesapeake Bay Watershed Agreement to restore and conserve ancestral lands and waters in the Chesapeake Bay region toward the goals of this Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the ICC will provide services such as participating in meetings and convenings, tracking progress toward protecting and restoring tribal lands in alignment with Agreement goals, and securing funding to support the capacity-building programs of its Tribal Nation members; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe's participation in the ICC will commence only with our Free, Prior, and Informed Consent and in ways that do not undermine our tribal sovereignty and self-determination, nor the obligation for formal government-to-government consultation on issues of concern to the Upper Mattaponi Tribe.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribe supports the vision of the ICC where Tribal Nations in the Chesapeake region are leading rematriation efforts of ancestral landscapes in ways that support the care, repair, and Indigenous connections needed to protect cultural heritage for future generations and supports the ICC as a future signatory of the Chesapeake Bay Watershed Agreement.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 6<sup>th</sup> day of November, 2025, at a Special Session with a vote of <u>6</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>1</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
