<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-01">
  <num>2025-01</num>
  <heading>Support for Tribal Heritage Grant Application</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-02-24</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-02-22</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-01.pdf">Res. No. 2025-01</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution to authorize the Upper Mattaponi Tribe to pursue a Tribal Heritage Grant through the National Park Service, affirming the Tribe’s commitment to preserving and promoting cultural and historic resources for future generations.</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe Council held this 22 day of February, 2025, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(a)">Article VII, Section 4(a)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> vests legislative power in the Council, granting it the authority to enact laws and adopt resolutions, including those essential to preserving the Tribe's cultural heritage as a sovereign, federally recognized Tribe; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>as a sovereign nation, the Upper Mattaponi Tribe has the inherent right and responsibility to protect its historic, cultural, and ancestral sites, ensuring that preservation efforts are governed by the Tribe's values, customs, and traditions, rather than external authorities; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the National Historic Preservation Act of 1966 authorizes grants to federally recognized Indian Tribes through the National Park Service’s Tribal Heritage Grant program to support the preservation and promotion of cultural heritage and traditions, including the protection of oral histories, traditional practices, sacred and historic places, and the establishment of Tribal historic preservation offices; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe recognizes the importance of preserving its cultural and historic resources, including sacred sites, traditional practices, oral histories, and historic properties, for the benefit of current and future generations; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council supports the pursuit of external funding opportunities, such as the Tribal Heritage Grant, to advance the Tribe’s cultural preservation initiatives in a manner consistent with the Tribe’s sovereignty and self-determination;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council hereby authorizes the application for and administration of a Tribal Heritage Grant through the National Park Service, in anticipation of the establishment of a Cultural Department, to support eligible activities such as, but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Conducting oral history projects and documenting traditional knowledge, skills, lifeways, and cultural traditions to ensure their transmission to future generations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Providing training and education to build capacity for historic preservation practices, including survey methods, cultural resource management, and compliance with applicable federal laws;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Creating educational and interpretive materials that promote the Tribe’s cultural heritage through curricula, exhibits, and public outreach initiatives.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Council affirms its support for the efforts of the Upper Mattaponi Program Management Office (PMO) and relevant staff or consultants in preparing and submitting the grant application and in administering the grant upon its award, consistent with the requirements of the National Park Service and the National Historic Preservation Act.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Council directs all appropriate departments and personnel to collaborate as necessary to ensure the successful implementation of this initiative in accordance with the Tribe’s cultural values, strategic priorities, and applicable laws.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 22 day of February, 2025, at a General Meeting with a vote of <u>6</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>1</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Constitution of the Tribe.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
