<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-12">
  <num>2025-12</num>
  <heading>Blanket Authority for Limited Waiver of Immunity for the Lease of Property for Tribal Uses</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-09-29</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-09-07</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-12.pdf">Res. No. 2025-12</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution to approve and authorize the Chief or his designee to execute a limited waiver of sovereign immunity in relation to certain lease agreements for the lease of property for Tribal uses, effective for two (2) years.</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council held this 27<sup>th</sup> day of September, 2025, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (the "Tribe") is an Indian Tribe that has existed from time immemorial and is federally recognized on a government-to-government basis by the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe has the authority, pursuant to the limitations of its laws and <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> (the "<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>"), to enter into contractual agreements, to buy, sell, and lease land, and among other things, to waive its sovereign immunity for purposes thereof; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>through its leadership, the Tribe wishes from time to time to lease property from Tribal uses; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the leadership of the Tribe has determined that leasing property for Tribal uses provides a substantial benefit or advantage to the Tribe, as it aligns with the Tribe's goals; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>entering into Lease Agreements for property requires the execution the Contract and various agreements, certifications, statements, affidavits, and other similar documents, which may be necessary and convenient; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the lease of property often requires a limited waiver of sovereign immunity and the applicability of the laws of other jurisdictions to consummate the Agreements; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite> provides, "Only the Council and Chief may authorize a waiver of Sovereign Immunity by law enacted in accordance with the Legislative Process.  Any authorization by the Council to waive Sovereign Immunity shall be specific, for a limited scope and duration, and in writing."  See, <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="XIII|1">Constitution, Article XIII, Section 1</cite>.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby authorizes the Chief for two (2) years from the date of this resolution to a Tribal Waiver of Immunity and Consent (the "Waiver"), subject to the following limitations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The term of the Lease Agreement does not exceed ten (10) years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The rental rate of the Lease is consistent with the prevailing rental rate of a similarly situated property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The Waiver's duration is limited to the duration of the Lease Agreement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The Waiver applies solely to any suit, action, or proceeding arising out of or brought to enforce the Tribe's obligations under the Lease Agreement provided such suit only occurs in a suitable in State court for Virginia; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>This Waiver shall apply only to any suit, action, or proceeding in State court; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>This Waiver is to be construed in accordance with federal law, and proceedings brought pursuant to this waiver shall be governed by laws as set forth in the Contract.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 27<sup>th</sup> day of September, 2025, at a General Meeting with a vote of <u>7</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
