<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-11">
  <num>2025-11</num>
  <heading>Supporting Upper Mattaponi Tribal Youth Council</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-09-29</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-09-07</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-11.pdf">Res. No. 2025-11</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution to authorize and support the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Youth Council's membership in UNITY, United National Indian Tribal Youth, Inc., to enhance youth leadership, cultural preservation, and community engagement.,</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council held this 27<sup>th</sup> day of September, 2025, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe') is a federally recognized Indian nation with inherent powers of self-governance; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Youth Council ("TYC") is an established body representing the youth citizens of the Tribe, whose mission is to engage tribal youth by encouraging participation in tribal activities, nurturing an understanding of tribal governance, and building a strong sense of cultural heritage; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the TYC envisions a future where young citizens are connected to their heritage, actively involved in tribal life, and working together as the next generation of leaders, grounded in the values of solidarity, perseverance, involvement, respect, integrity, and tradition; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the United National Indian Tribal Youth, Inc. ("UNITY") is a national organization dedicated to fostering the spiritual, mental, physical, and social development of American Indian, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian youth, supporting the growth of strong, unified, and self-reliant Native communities through youth leadership development, cultural preservation, and civic engagement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>UNITY provides a national network of affiliated youth councils, offering leadership development training, peer mentorship, cultural exchange, and opportunities for tribal youth to participate in regional and national advocacy efforts; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>joining UNITY will support the TYC's mission and vision by connecting its members to a broader community of Native youth leaders, expanding opportunities for leadership training, networking, cultural sharing, and community building; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the TYC has expressed its desire and commitment to formally join UNITY and participate actively in its programs and initiatives; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council ("Council") recognizes the importance of supporting the empowerment and leadership development of tribal youth and affirms its support for the TYC's engagement with UNITY.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council hereby authorizes and supports the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Youth Council's application for membership in UNITY, United National Indian Tribal Youth, Inc., and encourages continued participation in programs that promote youth leadership, education, cultural preservation, and community service.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council acknowledges that any required membership dues or associated costs for participation in UNITY shall be coordinated through the appropriate tribal budgetary process, subject to availability of funds and in accordance with tribal financial policies.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>this resolution shall take effect immediately upon adoption by the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 27<sup>th</sup> day of September 2025, at a General Meeting with a vote of <u>7</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
