<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2025-10">
  <num>2025-10</num>
  <heading>Authorization of Elder Care Title Vi Grant Application</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-09-12</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-09-11</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-10.pdf">Res. No. 2025-10</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>A Resolution authorizing the application for Elder Services funding from the Administration for Community Living/Administration on Aging Older Americans Act Title VI Nutrition, Supportive Service and Caregiver Grants (Parts A/B and C) and participation in Cycle IX of the National Resources Center on Native American Aging Needs Assessment "Identifying Our Needs: A Survey Of Elders".</text>
  <text>At a duly called Special Session of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council held this 11<sup>th</sup> day of September, 2025, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe") is a federally recognized Tribe existing and acting pursuant to its inherent and retained sovereignty; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4">Article VII, Section 4</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>, the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council ("Council") is vested with the legislative power of the Tribe, including the authority to enact laws and Budget Resolutions, and to raise revenue and appropriate funds for expenditure; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The National Resource Center on Native American Aging is supported by a cooperative agreement with the Administration for Community Living (ACL) of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) to identify the needs of American Indian, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian Elders nationwide via the needs assessment, in which the NRCNAA and the Tribe assume the following responsibilities;</text>
      <text>
        <u>The NRCNAA will provide:</u>
      </text>
      <text>Needs assessment instruments, assistance in sampling, training of interviewers, technical assistance with interviewers via email or telephone, data entry and analysis, data storage on a secure server, production of tables and comparisons with national statistics; and,</text>
      <text>
        <u>The Tribe will provide:</u>
      </text>
      <text>A Tribal Resolution documenting participation in the needs assessment, a count of Elders, interviewers or volunteers to conduct the survey, interpretation of the results with local input, development of recommendations for actions, dissemination of the results to Tribal leaders and health officials; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Summary information from needs assessment along with a national comparison report will be returned to the governing council and to the local contact person; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Data sovereignty, confidentiality, and safeguarding is of utmost importance; therefore, the information is collected anonymously, data is stored on a secure server for the life of the NRCNAA, and physical copies of the needs assessments will be stored within a locked storage cabinet at the University of North Dakota (UND) School of Medicine &amp; Health Sciences for a period of ten years as outlined in the UND's Records and Retention Schedule.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribe respectfully requests funding for the Administration for Community Living/Administration on Aging Older Americans Act Title VI grants (Parts A/B and C) for the grant period of April 1, 2026, to March 31, 2029. Additionally, the Council authorizes participation in the "Identifying Our Needs: A Survey of Elders" needs assessment and grants permission to the National Resource Center on Native American Aging to use all collected needs assessment information in an aggregate format for disseminating state, regional, and national results from analyses of the data.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that specific information collected within the boundaries of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe belongs to the Upper Mattaponi Tribe and may not be released in any form to individuals, agencies, or organizations without additional Tribal authorization.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 11<sup>th</sup> day of September, 2025, at a Special Session with a vote of  <u>0</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
