<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2023-014">
  <num>2023-014</num>
  <heading>Authorization of Health Department Selection of General Contractor – Aylett Dental Project</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-01-02</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-12-23</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2023-014.pdf">Res. No. 2023-014</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called Regular Meeting of the Council held this 23<sup>rd</sup> day of December, 2023, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the Council is vested with the authority to enact laws and Budget Resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VI|4|(a)">Article VI, Section 4(a)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> ("<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>"); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe")   operates a Health Department that provides a wide range of health services for the citizens of the Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Health Department issued an RFP to renovate building located at 8014 Richmond Tappahannock Hwy, Aylett VA for the Tribe's dental clinic; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the existing procurement policies of the Tribe require the Health Department to present its selection of a general contractor to the Council for final approval.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby enacts the attached law entitled, "AUTHORIZATION OF HEALTH DEPARTMENT SELECTION OF GENERAL CONTRACTOR".</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on December 23<sup>rd</sup>, 2023, at a Regular Meeting with a vote of <strong>3</strong> in favor and <strong>0</strong> opposed, <strong>1</strong> abstaining, and <strong>3</strong> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>______________________________</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Council</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <attachment id="law">
    <section>
      <num>1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text>This enactment shall be known as, the "AUTHORIZATION OF HEALTH DEPARTMENT SELECTION OF GENERAL CONTRACTOR – AYLETT DENTAL PROJECT".</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.2</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Council is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to the Council is vested with the authority to enact laws and Budget Resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VI|4|(a)">Article VI, Section 4(a)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> ("<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>"); and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Tribe operates a Health Department that provides a wide range of health services for the citizens of the Tribe; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>the Health Department issued a Request for Proposals ("RFP") for a general contractor to perform the renovation of an existing building located at 8014 Richmond Tappahannock Highway, Aylett VA for the Tribe's dental clinic; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>the existing procurement policies of the Tribe require the Health Department to present its selection of a billing services contractor to the Council for final approval.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.3</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of this Act is to authorize the Chief and the Health Department to select a billing services contractor to assist with the billing services that are necessary for the operation and administration of the Health Department.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.4</num>
      <heading>Authorization to Enter Into 638-Contracts</heading>
      <text>The Council hereby authorizes the Chief and the Health Department select a general Contractor based on the RFP responses received by the Tribe, and to negotiate and execute a contract with the general contractor selected by the Chief and Health Department.</text>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
