<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-05">
  <num>2026-05</num>
  <heading>Waiver of General Procurement Process for the Cannabis Business Project</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-03-03</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-02-28</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2026-05.pdf">Res. No. 2026-05</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution authorizing a limited waiver of existing Procurement Procedures to expedite contracting for the Tribe's Cannabis Business Project in accordance with the approved business plan.</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council held this 28<sup>th</sup> day of February, 2026, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe (the "Tribe") is an Indian Tribe that has existed from time immemorial and is federally recognized on a government-to-government basis by the United States of America; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> (the "<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>") was adopted to ensure the Tribe's well-being by fostering self-sufficiency, promoting sustainable development, and securing the economic future of the Tribe and its citizens; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(a)">Article VII, Section 4(a)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite> vests legislative power in the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council (the "Council") to enact laws and budget resolutions that support these interests; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in September 2023, the Tribe enacted the "Executive, Legislative, and Judicial Branches Contracting Authority Act of 2023", <cite doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribal Code of Law" path="4|§2103">UMT Code of Laws Title 4, Section 2103</cite>, which provides that the selection of vendors or contracting parties be done pursuant to the Tribe's procurement policies; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe has adopted specific Procurement Procedures to support the Tribe's operations and existing Healthcare Operations; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribe has developed a business plan for a key economic development opportunity for a Cannabis Business that rests on time to market and start-up of such operation will have stringent timelines.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby waives, specific to the Cannabis Business Project, the Procurement Procedures that are currently in place and authorizes the Chief, or their designee, to move forward with the needed procurement to deliver on the outlined Cannabis Business, provided that the Cannabis Business Project follows the business plan presented to the Council.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 28<sup>th</sup> day of February, 2026, at a General Meeting with a vote of <u>7</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
