<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-06">
  <num>2026-06</num>
  <heading>Authorization and Approval of Umt Heritage, LLC</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-03-13</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-03-12</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2026-06.pdf">Res. No. 2026-06</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution to authorize the formation of UMT Heritage, LLC as a wholly owned entity of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe and to approve its Articles of Organization and Operating Agreement.</text>
  <text>At a duly called Special Session of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council held this 12<sup>th</sup> day of March, 2026, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the Council is vested with the authority to enact laws and Budget Resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(a)">Article VII, Section 4(a) of the Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> ("Constitution"); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="XVI">Article XVI of the Constitution</cite>, "[t]he Tribe shall conduct business and economic development activities through a business entity or entities created by the Council by law;" and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>UMT Heritage, LLC has submitted to the Council its Articles of Organization and Operating Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to the submitted Articles of Organization and Operating Agreement, UMT Heritage, LLC is wholly owned by the Tribe with the Tribe as the sole owner; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to the submitted Articles of Organization, the effective date of UMT Heritage, LLC shall be on the date the Council enacts a resolution authorizing and approving the Articles of Organization; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text>the Council finds it in the best interests of the Tribe to create UMT Heritage, LLC.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Council hereby authorizes the formation of UMT Heritage, LLC, approves the attached "Articles of Organization of UMT Heritage, LLC", and approves the attached "Operating Agreement of UMT Heritage, LLC".  UMT Heritage, LLC, shall be considered an instrumentality of the Tribe and share in its immunity from suit as a sovereign nation.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>the Organizer of UMT Heritage, LLC, shall file executed versions of the attached "Articles of Organization of UMT Heritage, LLC" and "Operating Agreement of UMT Heritage, LLC," along with a fully executed version of this resolution with the Tribe's Department of Records Management.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on the 12<sup>th</sup> day of March 2026, at a Special Session with a vote of <u>7</u> in favor and <u>0</u> opposed, <u>0</u> abstaining, and <u>0</u> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite>.</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
