<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-04">
  <num>2026-04</num>
  <heading>Grant Fund Access to Support the ICC Project</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-03-03</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-02-28</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2026-04.pdf">Res. No. 2026-04</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution supporting participation in the ICC Project, "Empowering Tribal stewardship and capacity building for ecosystem market participation in the Chesapeake Bay watershed".</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council held this 28<sup>th</sup> day of February, 2026, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Chickahominy Indian Tribe, Chickahominy Indian Tribe - Eastern Division, Monacan Indian Nation, Nansemond Indian Nation, Pamunkey Indian Tribe, Rappahannock Tribe, and the Upper Mattaponi Tribe are all members of the Indigenous Conservation Council (ICC) of the Chesapeake Bay and have representation on its board of directors; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the ICC has secured funding from the US Department of Agriculture-Forest Service to support Tribal Nations in understanding and benefiting from revenue streams from private ecosystem markets through carbon credits, biodiversity credits, stewardship credits, wetland and/or  pollution credits  to protect tribal lands should they wish to do so; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>these revenue streams are currently being used by Tribal Nations around Turtle Island to develop long-term revenue while respecting tribal sovereignty and self-determination; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>participation in this project will not require any Tribal Nation to enter a private ecosystem market without their Free, Prior, and Informed Consent, and;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe agrees to participate in the proposed ICC project to build knowledge and support tools that increase forest, wetland, and soil health in alignment with Indigenous values and tribal sovereignty, and;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe identifies Chief and/or his designee(s) as participants in the project for engagement, training, and knowledge sharing,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council agrees to participate in the project entitled, GRANT 25-DG-11083150-111, "Empowering Tribal stewardship and capacity building for ecosystem market participation in the Chesapeake Bay watershed"</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
</document>
