<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2026-03">
  <num>2026-03</num>
  <heading>Supporting Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC Section 8(a) Participation</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-03-03</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-02-28</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2026-03.pdf">Res. No. 2026-03</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text class="center">A Resolution in support of Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC's participation in the Small Business Administration's Section 8(a) Program</text>
  <text>At a duly called General Meeting of the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council held this 28<sup>th</sup> day of February, 2026, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Upper Mattaponi Tribe ("Tribe") is an Indian Tribe that has existed from time immemorial and is federally recognized on a government-to-government basis by the United States of America under Section 303(a)(1) of the Thomasina E. Jordon Indian Tribes of Virginia Federal Recognition Act of 2017, Public Law No. 115-121 (January 29, 2018) ("Recognition Act"); and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII">Article VII</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe</cite> ("<cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>"), the Upper Mattaponi Tribal Council ("Council") is vested with the legislative power of the Tribe and has the authority to enact laws pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe" path="VII|4|(a)">Article VII, Section 4(a)</cite> of the <cite doc="Constitution of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe">Constitution</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC, was formed as a wholly owned company of the Tribe through adoption of <cite doc="Upper Mattaponi Tribe Res. No. 2024-08">Resolution 2024-08</cite> on June 22, 2024; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC, has acquired several contracts and is showing significant progress and potential as part of the Upper Mattaponi Tribe's on-going economic development goals; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>15 U.S.C. §§ 636(j)(10) and 637(a) authorizes the United States Small Business Administration to establish a business development program, commonly known as the 8(a) Business Development program.  Businesses, including tribal businesses, that participate in the program receive training and technical assistance designed to strengthen their ability to compete effectively in the American economy; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC, has indicated its desire to participate in the Small Business Administration's 8(a) Business Development program and requested the Tribe's support in this endeavor.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribe hereby indicates its full support of Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC's desire to apply for, and enter into, the Small Business Administration's 8(a) Business Development program; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Upper Mattaponi Tribe shall provide support of Upper Mattaponi Indian Tribe Technologies, LLC, as allowed by Upper Mattaponi Law, including the Tribe's budgetary process.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
</document>
